<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-09-13T17:58:51+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">NaNDay.dev Blog</title><subtitle>Life, thoughts, software engineering.</subtitle><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><entry><title type="html">Why investing shouldn’t be boring</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/05/19/why-personal-finance-shouldnt-be-boring.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why investing shouldn’t be boring" /><published>2023-05-19T12:48:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-19T12:48:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/05/19/why-personal-finance-shouldnt-be-boring</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/05/19/why-personal-finance-shouldnt-be-boring.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;vwce--chills-down-my-spine&quot;&gt;VWCE &amp;amp; Chill…s down my spine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’ve been moderator of an Italian subreddit about personal finance&lt;/strong&gt; for the last five years. It is the Italian subreddit &lt;a href=&quot;https://reddit.com/r/ItaliaPersonalFinance&quot; target=&quot;\_blank&quot;&gt;r/ItaliaPersonalFinance&lt;/a&gt;, and as you can guess, it is about the broad topic of personal finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot more than what people think when we talk about handling your cash nest and investing it. The favourite motto of the ItaliaPersonalFinance subreddit is “&lt;strong&gt;VWCE &amp;amp; Chill&lt;/strong&gt;”: just buy 100% VWCE (an ETF covering most of the developed and developing countries in the world, market-cap weighted), sit back and relax, while your money will eventually grow (in about 10 years time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the analogy that comes to mind, when thinking about “VWCE &amp;amp; Chill”, is getting prescribed generic pills at the first visit of a patient to their psychiatrist. The physician doesn’t know anything about the person in front of them, they don’t know their history, their thoughts, the depth of their possible illness, and still prescribe to “just take these pills and see how you feel”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may see some improvement, things can go nicely for a while; but in the end, the real effect of a mindless choice will manifest itself and blow in the face of the patient, that will visit another physician, maybe a better one, who will show the inner weakness of the choices of the first one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s to say, it’s not a bad idea &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt;. It’s a much better idea than going to your bank and make them invest your money (want to gift 3-8% of your invested money each year in commissions?). It’s an even better idea than just opening your brokerage account and then buying some random, popular stocks, and expect them to grow without a single drop. But it’s not what the Latins called a &lt;em&gt;panacea&lt;/em&gt;, a remedy for all possible personal finance issues. It’s more of a generic anti-inflammatory drug, to be administered with some care, and knowing we’re just treating symptoms, most of the times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough with the medicine metaphors: let’s dig into the issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-issues-with-generic-investments-advice&quot;&gt;Some issues with generic investments’ advice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everything’s changing faster than we realize&lt;/strong&gt;
As some old sage man once said, humans tend to think as if their present self, their current desiders, dreams, ambitions, etc., will never change again, if not for some smaller adaptations as we get older. When some folk on Reddit tells us “Only invest in stocks if you’re not going to touch this money for 10 years at least”, we find great joy in spending that money into VWCE, since the idea of the next 10 years of our life being stable and financially secure is appealing and pleases the self. But reality often unveils the lies we tell ourself… even in a traumatic way, sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Being young doesn’t automatically mean you should invest in stocks&lt;/strong&gt;
Common wisdom in the personal finance world tells us that young people should invest in stocks more (in percentage of their funds) than older folk. I think this is a huge simplification, and even plainly wrong in some cases.
In fact, I’m around 30 years old, and a lot changed in my life. Even something as my car, I sort of regret buying now, since I work from home and I don’t really need a vehicle in my own belongings any more. While five years ago I was absolutely certain I’d never own a house in my life, it looks like I will soon. And the list goes on.
&lt;strong&gt;Stocks are, from the return point of a view, very static assets&lt;/strong&gt;. You should generally own them for a long period of time before you can safely say they will have given something in return: stocks tend to live through long periods of slow growth, and sudden catastrophic free falls, before recovering. Bonds, on the other hand, unless the emitter defaults or “cuts” the promised coupons, have a very specific time-frame (even Bond ETFs… although it’s a bit more complicated).
Also, generally speaking, &lt;strong&gt;young people tend to have a low saving rate, due to salaries being lower, and the best investment they should make with the little money they have, is learning new skills and tools&lt;/strong&gt;, which can return a huge compound interest over time, instead of throwing the money into financial markets.
[For this specific idea, and the thoughts it provoked in me, I have to thank &lt;strong&gt;Paolo Coletti&lt;/strong&gt;, an Italian youtuber active in the finance and investments world.]
But, as always, looking at the average young person doesn’t provide answers for a lot of different people coming from different backgrounds, families, living in wildly different part of the world. Don’t just take the generic advice: it could be tragically wrong for you.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk aversion is a real thing, and nobody can really assess their own until things go south&lt;/strong&gt;
I think years of growing financial markets, especially with stocks, have altered the common perception of risk among everybody. I’ll make a gross simplification in the next lines, but bear with me: I think it’s needed as a wake up call for a lot of us.
&lt;strong&gt;Investing is stock is throwing your money at unknown people (the “market”), and expecting them to use it in unknown moves and make you earn more, but with no financial obligation to return any of the money given&lt;/strong&gt;. Imagine having 80 or 100% of your hard earned cash in the hands of these people. Does it feel safe?
How about bonds? &lt;strong&gt;Bonds are a contract, but still, a slim one&lt;/strong&gt;. There’s absolutely no guarantee the people you lend money to will effectively give it back. In the contract it is clearly stated that it’s their right to default on the promise, should things go wrong. And whether they’re using your money wisely or wasting it, is really out of your hands.
You’re betting on a bet safer than the casino’s, but still, it is betting. History of the last 50 years may show your bets are expected to give a nice premium. History of the last 100 years shows instead in what dangerous waters you’re swimming.
People &lt;strong&gt;can&lt;/strong&gt; and absolutely &lt;strong&gt;will&lt;/strong&gt; lose money when they’re betting. Not always, and that’s why we bet. And I’m not sure we can really assess our own risk aversion, just thinking about the hypotetical event of having our portfolio down 70% from when we bought it, unless we really are in that situation. Also because, it’s not like newspapers and media have a positive outlook on the economy when stock markets are so deep down the toilet: most probably, they’re talking about the end of finance as we know it, apocalypse and doom for the few crazy guys still holding stock ETFs. And it’s hard, almost impossible, to have a detached point of view and, instead of panic selling, buying more due to a one in a lifetime occasion of low prices.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wrapping-up&quot;&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not advocating for financial advisors: the reality is, most of us don’t have enough to be a customer for these people, and other solutions (robo advisors, or even, God forbid, bank advisors) are generally too expensive to be worth it (at least where I live). I think everybody should invest some time into learning personal finance and investments, but it’s probably just a distant dream. We’ll see: for the time being, I encourage you, my dear reader, to rethink your risk tolerance/aversion, your asset allocation, and be aware of the fact that our lives change, multiple times per decade, and it could be better for you to have an elasticity in your investments, instead of a complete, static commitment on the best returning asset class.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Personal finance" /><summary type="html">VWCE &amp;amp; Chill…s down my spine</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My experience with trading</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/03/18/my-experience-with-trading.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My experience with trading" /><published>2023-03-18T14:02:41+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-18T14:02:41+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/03/18/my-experience-with-trading</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/03/18/my-experience-with-trading.html">&lt;p&gt;Back in 2015, even before my whole professional career as a software engineer started, I became fascinated with the idea that, without even moving a single inch from my chair, &lt;strong&gt;I could become a profitable day-trader and just let that be my future full-time job&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea was born thanks to an Italian online community (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.finanzaonline.com&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Finanza OnLine&lt;/a&gt;), one of the most toxic yet fascinating communities in personal finance, investments and, for about 90% of the traffic of the website, “trading”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I gathered my hard-earned cash at the time (about 7k euros), opened a brokerage account in an Italian online bank, and…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, &lt;em&gt;of course&lt;/em&gt; it didn’t end well. With that meager budget, brokerage commissions counted for about 0,2% of every transaction. For a “day-trader”, it’s simply not sustainable, even if somehow I could manage to guess a trade at least 60% of times (&lt;em&gt;spoiler: I could not&lt;/em&gt;). &lt;strong&gt;I was chasing the gold fever, while my bank was selling me shovels&lt;/strong&gt; and making a very passive, simple profit out of my dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned a lot of terms and concepts day traders in the online community talk about. Technical analysis was one of them. Moving averages (simple, weighted…?), volumes, Relative Strength Index, MACD, and so on. I developed my own systems, but failed to even follow them consistently. I was just pursuing easy money, like a lottery, with a bit of a gambling habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I ended up losing about 2 or 3k&lt;/strong&gt;, can’t remember exactly. An overall expensive, yet cheap lesson, compared to what I could have lost years down the line, as a professional with a steady monthly income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And most importantly, after that experience, &lt;strong&gt;I had learned a bunch of useful stuff&lt;/strong&gt;. First of all, using an online broker to buy and sell stocks. The concepts of order limits, quantities, commissions, etc etc. Those all turned out to be quite handy, when studying investments and ETFs. Which I discovered in that same toxic community. There’s a very small, almost desert section of the forum about long-term investments and ETFs. And even though the content might not be much, discovering about the possibility of investing my own money with longer time horizons certainly started there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to trading. &lt;strong&gt;I didn’t actually abandon the whole idea of “trading” there&lt;/strong&gt;. Only one concept, which seemed interesting, stuck with me for a while. That concept is “algorithmic trading”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, I knew almost nothing about programming. I could probably set up an extremely simple HTML page, or write some code in Pascal, perhaps. So, while exploring this whole fascinating, perilous world, I even tried writing some algorithms for a while. I used a proprietary Italian software called VisualTrader, but it didn’t really stick, and I couldn’t find a decent way to make it work as I wanted (due to my own limits, not the platform’s), so I gave up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But years down the line, that idea came back. And then (about 2019), I could write complex programs! I had a look at some platforms, but in the end just wrote my own with barebone C# and .NET. The only external dependency was stocks data, which came for free from my broker at the time. Unfortunately, the broker changed rules after a while, and started charging about 20€/month for it - not worth it for me, since it was just a hobby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile though, I had developed a whole framework in .NET. It’s called &lt;strong&gt;Venice&lt;/strong&gt;, and its core library is actually &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/NandayDev/Venice&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;open-sourced on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t think anybody but me has ever used it, so, don’t expect it working out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did my algorithmic trading efforts go, by the way? Well, pretty poorly. Turns out in algo trading (as the cool kids call it), &lt;strong&gt;the hard part isn’t actually coding; it’s having a profitable idea which the market hasn’t already optimized away&lt;/strong&gt;. And with my simple trading systems, after commissions and taxes, I haven’t found nothing really worthy. At the moment, I’m only passively gathering one-minute stocks data every day from a Raspberry Pi, in the hope I make use of it one day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out maybe I should just do what I’m really good at, which is software engineering, and let dreams of passive income through trading fade away, for the time being.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Personal finance" /><summary type="html">Back in 2015, even before my whole professional career as a software engineer started, I became fascinated with the idea that, without even moving a single inch from my chair, I could become a profitable day-trader and just let that be my future full-time job.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Planning your life and finances: worth it?</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/thoughts/2023/01/26/planning-life-finances-worth-it.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Planning your life and finances: worth it?" /><published>2023-01-26T07:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-26T07:03:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/thoughts/2023/01/26/planning-life-finances-worth-it</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/thoughts/2023/01/26/planning-life-finances-worth-it.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;ips-investor-policy-statement&quot;&gt;IPS (Investor Policy Statement)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days, I’m setting some time aside to write my &lt;strong&gt;Investor Policy Statement (IPS)&lt;/strong&gt;, inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.retireinprogress.com&quot; target=&quot;\_blank&quot;&gt;Mr.RIP&lt;/a&gt;, an Italian blogger and content creator, and his recent update about his old IPS, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mr.rip/ips&quot; target=&quot;\_blank&quot;&gt;which you can find here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of an IPS, as I intend it throughout this post, should be to plan your investments years ahead, starting from some &lt;strong&gt;objectives&lt;/strong&gt;, then defining &lt;strong&gt;strategies&lt;/strong&gt;, and, in the end, an &lt;strong&gt;asset allocation&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;My objective is to reach retirement age around 65 years old with a decent safety nest of securities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;My strategy is putting aside 15% of my income and investing it in both index funds (or ETFs) and hand-picked stocks/bonds&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;My asset allocation is 40% stock ETFs, 20% single stocks, 40% single bonds&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. RIP also has a section about his philosophy of investments and investment details, but for simplicity I merged them into the strategy section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;objectives&quot;&gt;Objectives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s only one caveat to this whole architecture: the act of starting from objectives is, to say the least, weak. &lt;strong&gt;I believe objectives are not an endurable asset throughout your life&lt;/strong&gt;. Objectives mutate each year. I think Mr. RIP noticed this, since in &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/12ta_RURV99qFi0lxS-8Pgh5da3ee-XG9tWP1FHVST3c/edit&quot; target=&quot;\_blank&quot;&gt;his update to the IPS&lt;/a&gt;, his new objectives are a lot broader and more generic than the original IPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I’m coming to realize is this: &lt;strong&gt;planning and having specific objectives is not worth it&lt;/strong&gt;. Unless we’re talking about something coming up in the next year or so, thinking you can really pursue a very narrow objective for 10 or more years without rethinking it, is &lt;em&gt;usually&lt;/em&gt; wishful thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, the counterargument I usually hear is &lt;em&gt;Having an objective, and acting accordingly, is better than having none and just living day-by-day&lt;/em&gt;. At a first reading it seems correct. A purpose gives you strength: if that purpose changes through the way, you may still have accumulated some resources (money usually) to invest it elsewhere and follow another purpose. I kind of agree about having this flexibility. But I can’t help but think that maybe, &lt;strong&gt;what you should have followed instead, is having that flexibility&lt;/strong&gt;. Instead of giving yourself the illusion of an objective (“In 10 years time, I want to become financially independent!”), you could have planned something less specific, and reasonable (“In 10 years time, I want to have a good saving nest for whatever purpose I’ll find to spend part of it”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I understand, at this point, life would probably be emptier. As humans, we usually need a more powerful substance to fuel our life. Chasing the dream of opening that toys store where kids will come and cheer, instead of having the generic objective of being financially safe and flexible, sounds a lot better to our ears. And yet, I think for most of us, dreams and aspirations change each year. They rarely stick in a person’s life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;happiness&quot;&gt;Happiness…&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking in broader terms, &lt;strong&gt;if your purpose is being happy, that resolves to two aspects&lt;/strong&gt;, in the end:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pursuing what makes us happy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoiding what makes us unhappy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;strong&gt;while having a very specific objective certainly fullfills number 1 greatly, it fails spectacularly at number 2&lt;/strong&gt;. Chasing a dream is a road paved with difficulties and hardships. Doesn’t it make more sense to give up chasing a dream, and instead, just have some generic guidelines throughout your life? That way, you can still pursue happiness, while avoiding more moments of unhappiness along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-or-pain&quot;&gt;… or pain?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes. But…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we really wired that way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a fundamental question. If, as human beings, we’re just built to pursue very specific dreams and fullfillment, does it even make sense to try avoiding having those dreams?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Siddhartha Gautama, better known as the Buddha, would probably say yes. &lt;strong&gt;All the original buddhist philosophy (as far as I understand it) revolves around escaping Dharma, the perpetual rotating engine of desire, fullfillment and the pain it brings&lt;/strong&gt; (and of reincarnation in a more religious sense). Escaping desire surely seems like what we’re trying to achieve here. No dreams, just guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet, does it make sense? &lt;strong&gt;Isn’t the avoidance of pain, after all, pain&lt;/strong&gt;? Escaping Dharma is a struggle which could be eternal. How can I escape my own very instinctual nature, without a fight so intense it will probably bleed me out of all energies?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, &lt;strong&gt;accepting myself and my own nature seems more reasonable&lt;/strong&gt;. Life is struggle, life is pain. And the caveat here is, whenever I’m not struggling, my own self will suffer anyway: after a brief moment of joy, hedonism adaptation will kick in, and life will become boring in my eyes. And I shall move on again, back to another struggle. &lt;em&gt;“He who hesitates is lost”&lt;/em&gt;, they say, and for good reasons. Stasis kills the self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wrapping-up&quot;&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I may have derailed a bit here. I think, in the end, we can extract two key takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do have objectives&lt;/strong&gt;, because that’s what your brain is wired to do, and that’s what’s going to bring you joy in the short term; but beware of the fact that those objectives will surely change, sooner rather than later;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Save up resources&lt;/strong&gt; for your objectives, current or future ones: having that flexibility will help in any case.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Thoughts" /><summary type="html">IPS (Investor Policy Statement)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Travelling is nice, but I just don’t like it.</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/thoughts/2023/01/09/i-dont-like-travelling.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Travelling is nice, but I just don’t like it." /><published>2023-01-09T07:23:46+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-09T07:23:46+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/thoughts/2023/01/09/i-dont-like-travelling</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/thoughts/2023/01/09/i-dont-like-travelling.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As weird as it may sound, I don’t like travelling&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It comes from very far away. When I was a kid, my parents loved travelling. About once per year, we had these very long trips around Europe, in our camper. We went to pretty much every major European country, for about three weeks, and then came back. Sounds great, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I just couldn’t stand it. Being away from “my stuff”, my friends, my routines, was painful. I felt relieved when my parents decided it was enough, and started planning the road back home. My heart filled with joy when, from the A14 highway, I saw the “Ancona Nord” exit sign towards my hometown. During the trip, I must admit &lt;strong&gt;I was a dick&lt;/strong&gt;. I probably ruined the atmosphere some days, to the point that, when I became a bit older, the camper was sold and we stopped that habit of family journeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a bit painful to write. I can bear having small trips, one or two days of fun somewhere. I’m not &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; against sightseeing the world a little bit. But, for some reason any psychologist would probably cheerfully write essays about, the simple thought of leaving everything I have behind and staying away for weeks, just for the sake of “seeing the world”, is unbearable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not judging all of you people enjoying travelling. I understand it’s a big deal for almost everybody. At the same time, I’m sure I’m not the only one in the world not willing to join the “travelling tribe”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But aside from personal preferences, I’d like to explore the meaning which people give to travelling, most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That summer journey across a foreign country is seen, from most people I speak with, as the final reward for an year of pain and suffering. We pretty much try to ignore our boss’s unbearable behaviour, our colleague’s laziness, our significant other’s untidiness, since we know in a matter of months we’ll be on a beach &lt;em&gt;enjoying life&lt;/em&gt; while everybody else are probably thinking about how to ruin our life once we’re back (spoiler: he’ll probably be relaxing as you are).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this isn’t how I face life’s hardships. &lt;strong&gt;I’m not looking for an illusionary escape from the everyday gloom, because my everyday isn’t gloom at all&lt;/strong&gt;. I’m actually improving my daily journey, one step at a time, to the point I don’t need any sort of escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that feeling, though. When I was a full-time employee, a couple of years back, after a while seeing “Friday” on my phone’s lock screen filled me with relief. &lt;strong&gt;And that’s when I realized I had to leave that job&lt;/strong&gt;. As an employee, choices are out of your hands. You’re usually paid to bear with inefficiencies, hardships, people with bad temper. It’s complicated to stand up and be the agent of any kind of change. It’s all exchanged for a safe, nice salary, paid vacations and sick days, and so on. What everybody ends up doing (and me too), is just waiting for weekends and vacations to come, to find that little bit of distraction, even a sort of revenge (“Haha, now I’m taking these 20 paid days off and I won’t think about work for a single moment”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I’m pursuing a different life though, as a freelancer, &lt;strong&gt;I don’t really have that feeling anymore&lt;/strong&gt;. I like when Monday comes, and the week starts. I built my routine to be enjoyable. Should a point in time come when I’m feeling overwhelmingly negative about an engagement/gig/project, I’ll just leave it and find the next one. I’ve also built my finances to back me up in such a case: emergency funds are there exactly for this reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’m not sure this has anything to do with vacation, but the point is, I don’t have anything to run from&lt;/strong&gt;. All in all, I like my everyday life. When I feel it’s getting boring or repetitive or whatever, I change something of it, I don’t look into the future for the next escape. My friends and fiancee actually mock me because of this being “unrest”, incapable of stopping and enjoying life as it is; but I’m actually enjoying life, just improving it a little bit every month that passes by (or at least trying to; I don’t always take the right decisions, of course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll admit I’m too sedentary in this regard, and that probably having a week of just “going away” here and there would even benefit me. The thing is though, I don’t agree with the concept of vacations being escapes from reality. I think it’s misleading and overall sad, especially when the reality of your life is actually improveable. Maybe one day I’ll enjoy taking more time off, or even travelling while working, as it looks like a common thing now (for those of you who are Italian, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@Giuseppe.Funicello&quot;&gt;check out Giuppi’s channel about being a digital nomad&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until then, I’ll stick to my true self and enjoy life as it is. With few, short trips. My two parrots will thank me for being present!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Thoughts" /><summary type="html">As weird as it may sound, I don’t like travelling.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">About ‘growing’ up</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/thoughts/2023/01/05/about-growing-up.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="About ‘growing’ up" /><published>2023-01-05T22:52:50+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-05T22:52:50+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/thoughts/2023/01/05/about-growing-up</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/thoughts/2023/01/05/about-growing-up.html">&lt;p&gt;Just a little thought before going to bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Every moment of our life, we usually think we’re smarter than our self from a year ago&lt;/strong&gt;. There’s so much information/philosophy/life advice we try to digest, and elaborate, that sudden realizations make us rethink a lot about our choices and our approach, about once every few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the reality probably is, our brain has a limited RAM. That RAM can’t really expand, so at any given moment, we’re holding an amount of gigabytes of “life philosophy” that drive us, but when more of that stuff wants to enter in the RAM, the oldest data just ends up garbage collected. So, instead of improving our life with more and more data, what we’re probably doing is &lt;strong&gt;forgetting the oldest, less impactful thoughts we had, to replace it with new ones&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We like to think we’re &lt;em&gt;wiser&lt;/em&gt; than an year ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the reality probably is that we’re just &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Thoughts" /><summary type="html">Just a little thought before going to bed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Being a freelancer in the work-from-home era</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/career/2023/01/04/being-freelancer-work-from-home-era.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Being a freelancer in the work-from-home era" /><published>2023-01-04T19:34:08+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-04T19:34:08+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/career/2023/01/04/being-freelancer-work-from-home-era</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/career/2023/01/04/being-freelancer-work-from-home-era.html">&lt;p&gt;As you may know, &lt;strong&gt;in January 2022 I left my previous full-time employee job as a software engineer&lt;/strong&gt;, and opened a “partita iva” (VAT number), effectively becoming a proper, self-employed individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, I’ve had 5 clients so far, some for shorter projects, some for longer term engagements. I’m currently still working for the last one, and will probably still be until the end of February (after that, who knows!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2022 has gone really well in this regard&lt;/strong&gt;, making up for investments which have not shone at all..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll recap the route that brought me here where I am today - feel free to skip some sections if they bore you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-made-me-take-the-plunge&quot;&gt;What made me take the plunge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Going the freelance route isn’t a new thing for me&lt;/strong&gt;. Actually, aside from a period of “confusion” in my life, in which I did an internship for a Chinese travel agency both in Beijing and Rome, my work life began as a freelancer back in December 2016. So, this probably helped with the transition in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, there’s the motivation behind it, of course. When I left my previous freelance life, in January 2019, I did it for many reasons, but two were the most important:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A really good economic offer from the company I was collaborating with, as a freelancer;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A great team to work with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the first one faded quickly (curse you, hedonistic adaptation!), being in a great team lasted longer, and actually never changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot happened during those 3 years - I won’t enter into the details, in this post. What matters is, &lt;strong&gt;I realized I could have endured all the changes that we went through, as a team&lt;/strong&gt;. I could have just smiled and nodded, when facing the hard truth that &lt;strong&gt;as an employee, sometimes you have zero power over your work&lt;/strong&gt;, unless you decide to leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But I just couldn’t&lt;/strong&gt;. I was very close to leaving the company actually, around February 2020. Then Covid happened. Everybody braced for very hard times ahead, and having a job was a good place to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the moment when the whole world experienced working from home. Some of you may have struggled with that change; some have mixed feelings. I actually felt &lt;strong&gt;GREAT&lt;/strong&gt;. I picked it up immediately, and embraced it. Being able to work from home was a revelation for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, the hard Italian state-wide lockdown ended. Life changed. After an initial hesitation, everybody from the company was called back into the office 5/5 days, with less than 24 hours notice. I stupidly complied, without even moaning. &lt;strong&gt;I was miserable&lt;/strong&gt;. All the issues we had at the beginning of 2020, now mixed up with this forced work from the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll cut this short. In the end, for one reason or another, I was always looking for a change from that job. Apart from some smaller periods in which I even felt I could stay there longer term - brief illusions of freedom before the next thing happened - I was already mentally on my way out since 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 2021, &lt;strong&gt;I actually sent my resignation letter&lt;/strong&gt;. I had found an opportunity to work from home for a UK company. Yet, management convinced me of staying, with an economic incentive, responsibilities, and the possibility of working from home. I think it was the right thing to do at the time - but I’ll expand on this in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you may imagine, the illusion of staying there and fixing what wasn’t working only lasted for a while, before I left at the end of the year. Leaving the team, and the company, was hard. I’m not fit for goodbyes, or for keeping in touch with people in general. Since they didn’t find a replacement, and I gave a short notice, I agreed to stay as a part-time contractor with them for some months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summing up, &lt;strong&gt;I’m fairly convinced now of one thing: I just can’t bear the downsides of being an employee&lt;/strong&gt;. To be a good employee, you need some qualities I’m probably lacking. I’m proactive, scrupulous, but I also want to have agency in what I do, if I care for a product. I want to be autonomous. Maybe I was just unlucky with the work environment, who knows. But this is material for yet another post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-what-happened-in-2022&quot;&gt;So, what happened in 2022?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of 2022, the software engineer’s work landscape was still quite “hot”. Finding a gig was almost trivial. I picked up a smaller engagement, in which I was solo developing a proof of concept for an Android app. I loved working on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, &lt;strong&gt;I found myself working for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.angi.com&quot; target=&quot;\_blank&quot;&gt;Angi.com&lt;/a&gt; as an Android software engineer contractor&lt;/strong&gt;. The team in which I ended up was great. Shoutout to Nathan, my manager, who was just transitioning from being a lead developer to his new role. Really chill, competent guy, with 10 years of Android development on his back. And shoutout to my team too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it only lasted some months. The company wasn’t in great financial shape, and all contractors from the team were let go, including me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summer came, and also the contract with my previous employer ended. What followed was an unprecedented period in my life: I had earned quite a good amount in the last months, and I wasn’t really in need of finding another contract for a while. &lt;strong&gt;Heck, I could even stop working for 2022&lt;/strong&gt;! In hindsight, it lasted too little, for my own choices. After a couple of months developing my own projects, I felt some inner, irrational fear of being pushed out of the workforce by my own choices - the fear that I could not find another contract any time soon, since fears of a recession was looming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, finding another contract was pretty easy (not as easy as January, but still) and by the end of August I was back to business. Since then, I’ve been working in a quite chill team, with competent team leaders, and I’m pretty happy about it. But as I said, it wasn’t really necessary. Could have just waited until now: some less money in my bank accont, but a lot of time to pursue my projects - and &lt;a href=&quot;www.spookyparrots.com&quot; target=&quot;\_blank&quot;&gt;Spooky Parrots&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-about-the-financial-aspects&quot;&gt;What about the financial aspects?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a fiscal point of view, I’m in a flat-tax special regime in Italy called “Partita iva forfettaria”. It’s lightly taxed, with very little paperwork and bureaucracy, but comes at the cost of having a hardwired limit on your annual gross revenues. I achieved getting close to that limit, without exceeding it, so I take it as a win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is yet more material for another post: let’s just say it’s not convenient, unless you can reach very high revenues, to leave this flat-tax regime. At least for now, I won’t push towards that direction: this is a pretty comfy place to be, and I also have the financial excuse not to overwork during the year, and take some well earned rest periods. &lt;strong&gt;Burnout in our field is real&lt;/strong&gt;, especially for contractors, and &lt;strong&gt;especially for me&lt;/strong&gt;, since I tend to be very obsessed by finding solutions for problems, and not moving from my chair until “that issue is fixed” or “that feature is implemented”. So, long live the “partita iva forfettaria”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-are-the-differences-between-being-an-employee-and-a-freelancer&quot;&gt;What are the differences between being an employee and a freelancer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;in-my-day-to-day-job&quot;&gt;In my day-to-day job&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It really depends on what kind of freelancer you are&lt;/strong&gt;. The bigger part of my revenues, for instance, are made of daily contracting for a company. That’s to say, I’m paid a flat fee for each day of work, expected to work about 8 hours every day and ship features and bugfixing in a larger team. Not that different from being an employee, from that perspective. Usually those contracts last some months, and give you some peace of mind, although you can’t really stack them with other contracts of the same type. I mean, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/overemployed/&quot; target=&quot;\_blank&quot;&gt;it looks like some people do it&lt;/a&gt;, but I don’t even want to think about the implications and the possibility of burning out quickly, so thanks, but no thanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you can stack though is one-off gigs, as a proper freelancer&lt;/strong&gt;. Those jobs are usually for smaller companies, or even individuals, in which you agree to build a certain app/service/feature for a given amount of money. I tend to avoid them, unless I know really well the client and their needs. There’s a reason estimates are hard - and estimating my effort while signing a contract which clearly states I won’t get more than X money, no matter how many hours per day I’ll push into the job, isn’t easy. Also, getting paid with these projects is harder. Another post will come with tips, and the issues I encountered which (alas) made me discover those tips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;financially-speaking&quot;&gt;Financially speaking&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m paid more than I was as an employee, of course, but with less certainty. Apart from a vague threat of taking somebody to court, should they not pay, &lt;strong&gt;there isn’t much that forces your clients to pay the bills&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s all about relationships: if you do a good job, in software engineering there’s almost always need for further developments, so clients will tend to pay you. Not always on time though: your bill always comes after paying salaries, in a hierarchical perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another point is I’m left alone with my pension planning (I’m still contributing to the mandatory pension, but a lot less, and I’m not sure I’ll ever see that money again…), and there’s no “TFR”, which is a sort of Italian “severance” pay. In Italy TFR is mandatory, paid at the end of your employment (no matter the reason you left the company), and consists of about one month salary per year of employment, with some interests accumulated based partially on inflation. There’s no such thing for a contractor of course, so it has to be counted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I get ill and can’t work, I’ll simply won’t be paid as long as the illness lasts. Same thing goes for vacations. In general, what I found out is you have much more freedom on how many days to take off: since those days off are not compensated, it’s easier for the client to just let you take your time when needed. Of course, with moderation, or you may end up replaced. And &lt;strong&gt;replacing you, from a bureaucratic point of view, is way, way easier than an employee&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-about-freedom&quot;&gt;What about freedom?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More freedom, but &lt;strong&gt;not the Nirvana employees may imagine&lt;/strong&gt;. A lot of responsibility attached to that. Take the wrong steps, and you may end up in a bad place. Just consider you’re not legally shielded from your clients, and since you’ve not incorporated, your own assets are on the line when things go south. You’ve been warned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;but-work-from-home&quot;&gt;But, work from home?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, yes. Since the pandemic, almost all freelancers in software engineering just work from home. It was partially true even before, but some companies made those contractors come in the office to join their employees. Since 2020, not any more. &lt;strong&gt;Everybody and their mother work from home now&lt;/strong&gt;. Italy seems a bit behind on that from what I see, but I had no opportunities as a contractor thrown at me which implied going even one day per week into the office. &lt;em&gt;It just doesn’t make sense any more, especially for freelancers&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;im-thinking-of-leaving-my-full-time-job-now-should-i-do-it&quot;&gt;I’m thinking of leaving my full-time job now! Should I do it?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope I wrote quite a comprehensive “guide” in the above paragraphs, although I just reported my personal experience. But let me clear this up: your first answer should be &lt;strong&gt;absolutely not&lt;/strong&gt;, unless:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You really hate being an employee&lt;/strong&gt;. Not just your current or your previous job: you have to look deep inside yourself, and realize you’re not made for this work arrangement of receiving a very safe salary and giving up your 8 hours per day to whatever it’s needed. I mean, it’s not even that different as a daily contractor!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’re financially covered&lt;/strong&gt;. I’d never have made the leap without good savings to cover my arse.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You have one or more certain opportunity ahead&lt;/strong&gt;. Some of your acquaintances (not friends, please!) in need of your skillset, or really any kind of safe project with which to start. Even your previous employer, for a while, if you leave on good terms.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You know what you’re risking&lt;/strong&gt;. Not much to say. As a freelancer, you’re free to empower yourself and earn plenty, as well as shooting yourself in the foot and die crying - financially speaking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-words&quot;&gt;Final words&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I’m pretty happy of this first year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’ve earned quite well&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’ve worked less&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have a much greater peace of mind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I would do differently:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No need to rush looking for the next opportunity when your yearly revenues are already high: could have taken more time off&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Properly written, arse-covering contracts are more important than I think&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’m not optimistic though. Weird times are coming ahead, with inflation, tech bubble bursting, layoffs, etc.&lt;/strong&gt; Plus, this new life is still a bit new to me; given enough time, I know I could grow unsatisfied, and look for another change in the future. Who knows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading so far. I really hope you found some insights in my words. If not, ah, whatever.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Career" /><summary type="html">As you may know, in January 2022 I left my previous full-time employee job as a software engineer, and opened a “partita iva” (VAT number), effectively becoming a proper, self-employed individual.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">About FIRE</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/01/03/about-fire.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="About FIRE" /><published>2023-01-03T07:25:10+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-03T07:25:10+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/01/03/about-fire</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/01/03/about-fire.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I like FIRE&lt;/strong&gt;. I mean, when I read about it in 2015ish, somewhere around Reddit, it seemed like a great idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FIRE: Financial Independence, Retire Early. I’m not going to explain it. If you don’t know what it is about, check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/f/financial-independence-retire-early-fire.asp&quot;&gt;this page from Investopedia&lt;/a&gt; and then come back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There are only some people on Earth capable of pursuing such a dream, and in the end be happy with their choice for a long time&lt;/strong&gt; – until they die, usually.
But most human beings wouldn’t be able to deal with the abnormal consequences FIRE determines. For their lives would suddenly be emptied of certainties, their unspeakable freedom depressingly unenjoyable, since all their friends would be too busy working, spending money and envying them.
Only some rational, lateral-thinking folks are going to seriously try to pursue FIRE; a very small subset of them will achieve it, given how life changes at every turn; but being frugal and smart passive-investors won’t make them good candidates for a complete FIRE life.
&lt;strong&gt;Most of them would probably be better off pursuing some kind of intermediate achievement&lt;/strong&gt;, like amassing enough wealth to pick up a part-time job, and enjoying some more degrees of freedom instead of a full-fledged, totalizing FIRE experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand my statements may sound strong, or even wrong, for some. Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people you and I know have a job. Most people’s jobs are average, with average duties, and average salaries (of course); they usually have an idea of how much they earn, and a very vague notion of their actual spending. These people may save something, but it’s usually just a small nest ready to be depleted with the first vacation, a siny four-wheels, or a new Fabolous-Sized TV. They are bound to their wages. Being this sort of modern slave isn’t too bad after all: it’s culturally acceptable, everybody does the same, and thus very few seriously plan for alternative paths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Now imagine their shock, when somebody, who they thought, after all, was a member of their social group, accepting their same rules and destiny, suddenly breaks free of those shackles&lt;/strong&gt;. Imagine this person coming back from a short interview with HR to pack their stuff. “I’m done, I’m leaving.” “Oh, wow… did you find a better paying job?” “No, I’m done. For good.” “Well… you must have something lined up!” “Nothing’s lined up. Goodbye.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t EXPECTED. This isn’t NORMAL. This isn’t… FAIR. &lt;strong&gt;Congratulations, you’ve suddenly become a pariah&lt;/strong&gt;. A lottery winner, who’s going to lose all their previous friends, their fellow mariners in perilous waters, to take an emergency motorboat to Hawaai.
You’re a danger to the status quo. In evolutionary terms, as “The Elephant In The Brain” cleverly points out, you’re a norm violator. &lt;strong&gt;You just broke the unspoken rule of being a wage slave&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you may lie. You may tell them you found another job, that gives you more “freedom”. They’re going to envy you a bit, but you’re going to stay into their social circle, just a bit farther than their center. But lying won’t help in creating lasting relationships. We’re not wired to lie to our closest peers. And guess what, probably most of your closest peers won’t pursue financial independence, now nor never.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you, &lt;strong&gt;loneliness isn’t for everyone&lt;/strong&gt;. Now imagine: you live a life of frugality and giving up, just to find yourself devoid of friends and people with whom to speak. Is it really desirable? Plus, don’t forget you’re not even in possession of a fat bank account to buy back some of that entertainment. I mean, you have it, but you can’t spend it, otherwise your dream is going to be shattered in a matter of months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not saying you’re doomed to fail, or that nobody at all should pursue FIRE. But well before starting to cut expenses and fill spreadsheets, there should be a solid plan in place. You should probably embark on this journey with someone else – and I’m talking about a friend, a close one, with whom life won’t change after FIRE, apart from seeing him/her more often. I wouldn’t recommend a partner – should something break your relationship, your FIRE plan would probably blow up too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Know your limits as a human being. Don’t underestimate the power of shame, of culture, of being in a society. Your FIRE plan must be sustainable under all aspects:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financially (of course)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Socially&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Psychologically
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I have at least some friends who would totally accept me being unemployed and financially independent, and still frugal?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I have at least a friend who would join me in this journey?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Does my SO understand and accept?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Etc…&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without those basics covered, FIRE is not something I’d pursue, not now, not ever.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Personal finance" /><summary type="html">I like FIRE. I mean, when I read about it in 2015ish, somewhere around Reddit, it seemed like a great idea.</summary></entry></feed>