<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-01-04T10:08:17+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Feliciter</title><subtitle>NaNDay's messy blog</subtitle><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><entry><title type="html">About FIRE</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/01/03/about-fire.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="About FIRE" /><published>2023-01-03T07:25:10+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-03T07:25:10+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/01/03/about-fire</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/01/03/about-fire.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I like FIRE&lt;/strong&gt;. I mean, when I read about it in 2015ish, somewhere around Reddit, it seemed like a great idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FIRE: Financial Independence, Retire Early. I’m not going to explain it. If you don’t know what it is about, check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/f/financial-independence-retire-early-fire.asp&quot;&gt;this page from Investopedia&lt;/a&gt; and then come back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There are only some people on Earth capable of pursuing such a dream, and in the end be happy with their choice for a long time&lt;/strong&gt; – until they die, usually.
But most human beings wouldn’t be able to deal with the abnormal consequences FIRE determines. For their lives would suddenly be emptied of certainties, their unspeakable freedom depressingly unenjoyable, since all their friends would be too busy working, spending money and envying them.
Only some rational, lateral-thinking folks are going to seriously try to pursue FIRE; a very small subset of them will achieve it, given how life changes at every turn; but being frugal and smart passive-investors won’t make them good candidates for a complete FIRE life.
&lt;strong&gt;Most of them would probably be better off pursuing some kind of intermediate achievement&lt;/strong&gt;, like amassing enough wealth to pick up a part-time job, and enjoying some more degrees of freedom instead of a full-fledged, totalizing FIRE experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand my statements may sound strong, or even wrong, for some. Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people you and I know have a job. Most people’s jobs are average, with average duties, and average salaries (of course); they usually have an idea of how much they earn, and a very vague notion of their actual spending. These people may save something, but it’s usually just a small nest ready to be depleted with the first vacation, a siny four-wheels, or a new Fabolous-Sized TV. They are bound to their wages. Being this sort of modern slave isn’t too bad after all: it’s culturally acceptable, everybody does the same, and thus very few seriously plan for alternative paths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Now imagine their shock, when somebody, who they thought, after all, was a member of their social group, accepting their same rules and destiny, suddenly breaks free of those shackles&lt;/strong&gt;. Imagine this person coming back from a short interview with HR to pack their stuff. “I’m done, I’m leaving.” “Oh, wow… did you find a better paying job?” “No, I’m done. For good.” “Well… you must have something lined up!” “Nothing’s lined up. Goodbye.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t EXPECTED. This isn’t NORMAL. This isn’t… FAIR. &lt;strong&gt;Congratulations, you’ve suddenly become a pariah&lt;/strong&gt;. A lottery winner, who’s going to lose all their previous friends, their fellow mariners in perilous waters, to take an emergency motorboat to Hawaai.
You’re a danger to the status quo. In evolutionary terms, as “The Elephant In The Brain” cleverly points out, you’re a norm violator. &lt;strong&gt;You just broke the unspoken rule of being a wage slave&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you may lie. You may tell them you found another job, that gives you more “freedom”. They’re going to envy you a bit, but you’re going to stay into their social circle, just a bit farther than their center. But lying won’t help in creating lasting relationships. We’re not wired to lie to our closest peers. And guess what, probably most of your closest peers won’t pursue financial independence, now nor never.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you, &lt;strong&gt;loneliness isn’t for everyone&lt;/strong&gt;. Now imagine: you live a life of frugality and giving up, just to find yourself devoid of friends and people with whom to speak. Is it really desirable? Plus, don’t forget you’re not even in possession of a fat bank account to buy back some of that entertainment. I mean, you have it, but you can’t spend it, otherwise your dream is going to be shattered in a matter of months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not saying you’re doomed to fail, or that nobody at all should pursue FIRE. But well before starting to cut expenses and fill spreadsheets, there should be a solid plan in place. You should probably embark on this journey with someone else – and I’m talking about a friend, a close one, with whom life won’t change after FIRE, apart from seeing him/her more often. I wouldn’t recommend a partner – should something break your relationship, your FIRE plan would probably blow up too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Know your limits as a human being. Don’t underestimate the power of shame, of culture, of being in a society. Your FIRE plan must be sustainable under all aspects:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financially (of course)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Socially&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Psychologically
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I have at least some friends who would totally accept me being unemployed and financially independent, and still frugal?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I have at least a friend who would join me in this journey?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Does my SO understand and accept?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Etc…&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without those basics covered, FIRE is not something I’d pursue, not now, not ever.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Personal finance" /><summary type="html">I like FIRE. I mean, when I read about it in 2015ish, somewhere around Reddit, it seemed like a great idea.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My story - Living the dream, until the Recession hit: 1 to 19 years old</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/my%20story/2022/10/14/my-personal-story-part-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My story - Living the dream, until the Recession hit: 1 to 19 years old" /><published>2022-10-14T12:42:56+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-14T12:42:56+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/my%20story/2022/10/14/my-personal-story-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/my%20story/2022/10/14/my-personal-story-part-1.html">&lt;p&gt;My story starts in the 90s, in a town in central Italy, not too far from the seaside, in a beautiful landscape of hills and historical remembrances, but also a pretty dynamic industrial hub.
The town I was born in was, and still is, an average sized town for Italy, of around 40 thousand inhabitants.
The first neighbourhood I have fond memories of, is a pretty green, well-served place not too far from the city centre. Lots of families, and friends around my age to play football (soccer!) with. Life was great.
I was born in a higher-middle class family, both traditional and liberal, so to say. My father worked as an entrepreneur, while my mother had a more classic 9-to-5 job.
My parents did pretty well overall. The 90s in Italy were probably the last decade of “wellbeing” for our economy, although not even close to the roaring growth we experienced in the 60s, 70s and 80s.
I was educated as a proper catholic, and even served as an altar boy for some years, with our local community. I only have good memories of the two priests who managed that church, and I’m a bit sad that I’ve lost my faith over the years – I can define myself as an agnostic individual, towards faiths in general.
Anyway, I attended primary school both mornings and afternoons, apart from Wednesdays and Saturdays (and of course Sundays we were free!). Since my parents had a pretty busy working life, I spent a lot of time with my grandma.
Of course, there would be a lot to write about, but I think it’d end up boring you, my reader. Nice memories for myself, good for a diary maybe, but not a public blog.
The most interesting part to highlight is probably my family’s finances. As I said, my parents were in pretty good shape. We had a nice apartment, went for some vacations abroad every year (which I hated… sorry, that’s how I am), and I had access to PCs, consoles, bikes, and so on. I think my father was leaning towards saving money most of the time, and my mother sometimes argued with him about that, but not in front of us kids.
I was given a weekly allowance of 10 thousand lire, which is the equivalent, in today’s money, of roughly 10 euros. I spent all of it, each time. Saving for something wasn’t in my mind, and although my father tried to teach me, for some reason it didn’t stick. At the times, I was a &lt;i&gt;spendaccione&lt;i&gt;, rather than a money saver.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Italy, the 2000s eras began with some historical changes. In 2002, starting January 1st, the Euro currency suddenly appeared. I remember being at a &lt;i&gt;tabaccaio&lt;i&gt; (a common shop in Italy, selling tobacco, stamps, lottery tickets and so on), and being given these weird coins as change for my lire… and being a bit puzzled about their appearance.
In my personal life, I graduated from primary school (there was a sort of exam at the time, now I think they just deleted it) and went to scuola media (middle school).
During these times, I started to change a bit. An ADSL, meaning “broadband internet”, was installed in our home. I started playing videogames in a more intense manner than before, and playing online with strangers became my thing. My parents became increasingly worried, for good reasons, and started fighting my addiction for video games, limiting my time I had access to the PC.
The Italian economy kept growing, as well as house prices. &lt;i&gt;Investi nel mattone&lt;i&gt; (“Invest into real estate”) was the motto of every living adult in Italy. Stocks plummeted in 2000-2001, while houses were still greatly priced! What could go wrong, if you had a nice set of bricks instead of volatile financial products in your pockets?
Anyway, my world, already endangered, fell apart completely from 2008. People started talking about this “crisis”, this “recession” thing. Strange, scary words we had never heard before, in our blind wellbeing over the years. My father worked in a pretty exposed field (yes… houses), and had just taken huge loans for a &lt;i&gt;monstre&lt;i&gt; project, which would have made us rich, prosperous, step up in the Olympus! … and actually, brought only troubles.
Things went south quickly. The Italian financial markets turned out to be inflated (a lot!), in a gigantic bubble which popped silently at first, and then devastated our country as months passed by. It was like watching a nuclear explosion from space, and then realizing you were actually too close to it. You may all know the effect of a recession, but what you may have not experienced, is the feeling of a crisis which still hasn’t passed, still looming, alongside fear and regrets. To put it into perspective, while the S&amp;amp;P 500 recovered historical highs and doubled it, our index, the Italian FTSE MIB, is still 50% lower than the 2007 peak. Of course, our index is not a total return one, (meaning, a stock index in which dividends are accounted for). Our equivalent, the FTSE MIB TR, has only very recently reached the 2007 peak, and is already going down these weeks.
In 2009, after graduating from high school, I decided I had enough of my life and town so far, and took off, thanks to some savings my father had accumulated through the years. I went to Bologna’s university, one of the most well known in Italy, and started my academic life there. More about it in the next post of the series.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="My story" /><summary type="html">My story starts in the 90s, in a town in central Italy, not too far from the seaside, in a beautiful landscape of hills and historical remembrances, but also a pretty dynamic industrial hub. The town I was born in was, and still is, an average sized town for Italy, of around 40 thousand inhabitants. The first neighbourhood I have fond memories of, is a pretty green, well-served place not too far from the city centre. Lots of families, and friends around my age to play football (soccer!) with. Life was great. I was born in a higher-middle class family, both traditional and liberal, so to say. My father worked as an entrepreneur, while my mother had a more classic 9-to-5 job. My parents did pretty well overall. The 90s in Italy were probably the last decade of “wellbeing” for our economy, although not even close to the roaring growth we experienced in the 60s, 70s and 80s. I was educated as a proper catholic, and even served as an altar boy for some years, with our local community. I only have good memories of the two priests who managed that church, and I’m a bit sad that I’ve lost my faith over the years – I can define myself as an agnostic individual, towards faiths in general. Anyway, I attended primary school both mornings and afternoons, apart from Wednesdays and Saturdays (and of course Sundays we were free!). Since my parents had a pretty busy working life, I spent a lot of time with my grandma. Of course, there would be a lot to write about, but I think it’d end up boring you, my reader. Nice memories for myself, good for a diary maybe, but not a public blog. The most interesting part to highlight is probably my family’s finances. As I said, my parents were in pretty good shape. We had a nice apartment, went for some vacations abroad every year (which I hated… sorry, that’s how I am), and I had access to PCs, consoles, bikes, and so on. I think my father was leaning towards saving money most of the time, and my mother sometimes argued with him about that, but not in front of us kids. I was given a weekly allowance of 10 thousand lire, which is the equivalent, in today’s money, of roughly 10 euros. I spent all of it, each time. Saving for something wasn’t in my mind, and although my father tried to teach me, for some reason it didn’t stick. At the times, I was a spendaccione, rather than a money saver.</summary></entry></feed>