<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-01-04T23:31:46+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Feliciter</title><subtitle>NaNDay's messy blog</subtitle><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><entry><title type="html">Being a freelancer in the work-from-home era</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/career/2023/01/04/being-freelancer-work-from-home-era.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Being a freelancer in the work-from-home era" /><published>2023-01-04T19:34:08+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-04T19:34:08+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/career/2023/01/04/being-freelancer-work-from-home-era</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/career/2023/01/04/being-freelancer-work-from-home-era.html">&lt;p&gt;As you may know, &lt;strong&gt;in January 2022 I left my previous full-time employee job as a software engineer&lt;/strong&gt;, and opened a “partita iva” (VAT number), effectively becoming a proper, self-employed individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, I’ve had 5 clients so far, some for shorter projects, some for longer term engagements. I’m currently still working for the last one, and will probably still be until the end of February (after that, who knows!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2022 has gone really well in this regard&lt;/strong&gt;, making up for investments which have not shone at all..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll recap the route that brought me here where I am today - feel free to skip some sections if they bore you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-made-me-take-the-plunge&quot;&gt;What made me take the plunge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Going the freelance route isn’t a new thing for me&lt;/strong&gt;. Actually, aside from a period of “confusion” in my life, in which I did an internship for a Chinese travel agency both in Beijing and Rome, my work life began as a freelancer back in December 2016. So, this probably helped with the transition in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, there’s the motivation behind it, of course. When I left my previous freelance life, in January 2019, I did it for many reasons, but two were the most important:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A really good economic offer from the company I was collaborating with, as a freelancer;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A great team to work with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the first one faded quickly (curse you, hedonistic adaptation!), being in a great team lasted longer, and actually never changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot happened during those 3 years - I won’t enter into the details, in this post. What matters is, &lt;strong&gt;I realized I could have endured all the changes that we went through, as a team&lt;/strong&gt;. I could have just smiled and nodded, when facing the hard truth that &lt;strong&gt;as an employee, sometimes you have zero power over your work&lt;/strong&gt;, unless you decide to leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But I just couldn’t&lt;/strong&gt;. I was very close to leaving the company actually, around February 2020. Then Covid happened. Everybody braced for very hard times ahead, and having a job was a good place to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the moment when the whole world experienced working from home. Some of you may have struggled with that change; some have mixed feelings. I actually felt &lt;strong&gt;GREAT&lt;/strong&gt;. I picked it up immediately, and embraced it. Being able to work from home was a revelation for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, the hard Italian state-wide lockdown ended. Life changed. After an initial hesitation, everybody from the company was called back into the office 5/5 days, with less than 24 hours notice. I stupidly complied, without even moaning. &lt;strong&gt;I was miserable&lt;/strong&gt;. All the issues we had at the beginning of 2020, now mixed up with this forced work from the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll cut this short. In the end, for one reason or another, I was always looking for a change from that job. Apart from some smaller periods in which I even felt I could stay there longer term - brief illusions of freedom before the next thing happened - I was already mentally on my way out since 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 2021, &lt;strong&gt;I actually sent my resignation letter&lt;/strong&gt;. I had found an opportunity to work from home for a UK company. Yet, management convinced me of staying, with an economic incentive, responsibilities, and the possibility of working from home. I think it was the right thing to do at the time - but I’ll expand on this in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you may imagine, the illusion of staying there and fixing what wasn’t working only lasted for a while, before I left at the end of the year. Leaving the team, and the company, was hard. I’m not fit for goodbyes, or for keeping in touch with people in general. Since they didn’t find a replacement, and I gave a short notice, I agreed to stay as a part-time contractor with them for some months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summing up, &lt;strong&gt;I’m fairly convinced now of one thing: I just can’t bear the downsides of being an employee&lt;/strong&gt;. To be a good employee, you need some qualities I’m probably lacking. I’m proactive, scrupulous, but I also want to have agency in what I do, if I care for a product. I want to be autonomous. Maybe I was just unlucky with the work environment, who knows. But this is material for yet another post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-what-happened-in-2022&quot;&gt;So, what happened in 2022?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of 2022, the software engineer’s work landscape was still quite “hot”. Finding a gig was almost trivial. I picked up a smaller engagement, in which I was solo developing a proof of concept for an Android app. I loved working on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, &lt;strong&gt;I found myself working for &lt;a href=&quot;www.angi.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Angi.com&lt;/a&gt; as an Android software engineer contractor&lt;/strong&gt;. The team in which I ended up was great. Shoutout to Nathan, my manager, who was just transitioning from being a lead developer to his new role. Really chill, competent guy, with 10 years of Android development on his back. And shoutout to my team too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it only lasted some months. The company wasn’t in great financial shape, and all contractors from the team were let go, including me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summer came, and also the contract with my previous employer ended. What followed was an unprecedented period in my life: I had earned quite a good amount in the last months, and I wasn’t really in need of finding another contract for a while. &lt;strong&gt;Heck, I could even stop working for 2022&lt;/strong&gt;! In hindsight, it lasted too little, for my own choices. After a couple of months developing my own projects, I felt some inner, irrational fear of being pushed out of the workforce by my own choices - the fear that I could not find another contract any time soon, since fears of a recession was looming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, finding another contract was pretty easy (not as easy as January, but still) and by the end of August I was back to business. Since then, I’ve been working in a quite chill team, with competent team leaders, and I’m pretty happy about it. But as I said, it wasn’t really necessary. Could have just waited until now: some less money in my bank accont, but a lot of time to pursue my projects - and &lt;a href=&quot;www.spookyparrots.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Spooky Parrots&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-about-the-financial-aspects&quot;&gt;What about the financial aspects?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a fiscal point of view, I’m in a flat-tax special regime in Italy called “Partita iva forfettaria”. It’s lightly taxed, with very little paperwork and bureaucracy, but comes at the cost of having a hardwired limit on your annual gross revenues. I achieved getting close to that limit, without exceeding it, so I take it as a win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is yet more material for another post: let’s just say it’s not convenient, unless you can reach very high revenues, to leave this flat-tax regime. At least for now, I won’t push towards that direction: this is a pretty comfy place to be, and I also have the financial excuse not to overwork during the year, and take some well earned rest periods. &lt;strong&gt;Burnout in our field is real&lt;/strong&gt;, especially for contractors, and &lt;strong&gt;especially for me&lt;/strong&gt;, since I tend to be very obsessed by finding solutions for problems, and not moving from my chair until “that issue is fixed” or “that feature is implemented”. So, long live the “partita iva forfettaria”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-are-the-differences-between-being-an-employee-and-a-freelancer&quot;&gt;What are the differences between being an employee and a freelancer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;in-my-day-to-day-job&quot;&gt;In my day-to-day job&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It really depends on what kind of freelancer you are&lt;/strong&gt;. The bigger part of my revenues, for instance, are made of daily contracting for a company. That’s to say, I’m paid a flat fee for each day of work, expected to work about 8 hours every day and ship features and bugfixing in a larger team. Not that different from being an employee, from that perspective. Usually those contracts last some months, and give you some peace of mind, although you can’t really stack them with other contracts of the same type. I mean, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/overemployed/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;it looks like some people do it&lt;/a&gt;, but I don’t even want to think about the implications and the possibility of burning out quickly, so thanks, but no thanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you can stack though is one-off gigs, as a proper freelancer&lt;/strong&gt;. Those jobs are usually for smaller companies, or even individuals, in which you agree to build a certain app/service/feature for a given amount of money. I tend to avoid them, unless I know really well the client and their needs. There’s a reason estimates are hard - and estimating my effort while signing a contract which clearly states I won’t get more than X money, no matter how many hours per day I’ll push into the job, isn’t easy. Also, getting paid with these projects is harder. Another post will come with tips, and the issues I encountered which (alas) made me discover those tips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;financially-speaking&quot;&gt;Financially speaking&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m paid more than I was as an employee, of course, but with less certainty. Apart from a vague threat of taking somebody to court, should they not pay, &lt;strong&gt;there isn’t much that forces your clients to pay the bills&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s all about relationships: if you do a good job, in software engineering there’s almost always need for further developments, so clients will tend to pay you. Not always on time though: your bill always comes after paying salaries, in a hierarchical perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another point is I’m left alone with my pension planning (I’m still contributing to the mandatory pension, but a lot less, and I’m not sure I’ll ever see that money again…), and there’s no “TFR”, which is a sort of Italian “severance” pay. In Italy TFR is mandatory, paid at the end of your employment (no matter the reason you left the company), and consists of about one month salary per year of employment, with some interests accumulated based partially on inflation. There’s no such thing for a contractor of course, so it has to be counted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I get ill and can’t work, I’ll simply won’t be paid as long as the illness lasts. Same thing goes for vacations. In general, what I found out is you have much more freedom on how many days to take off: since those days off are not compensated, it’s easier for the client to just let you take your time when needed. Of course, with moderation, or you may end up replaced. And &lt;strong&gt;replacing you, from a bureaucratic point of view, is way, way easier than an employee&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-about-freedom&quot;&gt;What about freedom?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More freedom, but &lt;strong&gt;not the Nirvana employees may imagine&lt;/strong&gt;. A lot of responsibility attached to that. Take the wrong steps, and you may end up in a bad place. Just consider you’re not legally shielded from your clients, and since you’ve not incorporated, your own assets are on the line when things go south. You’ve been warned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;but-work-from-home&quot;&gt;But, work from home?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ah, yes. Since the pandemic, almost all freelancers in software engineering just work from home. It was partially true even before, but some companies made those contractors come in the office to join their employees. Since 2020, not any more. &lt;strong&gt;Everybody and their mother work from home now&lt;/strong&gt;. Italy seems a bit behind on that from what I see, but I had no opportunities as a contractor thrown at me which implied going even one day per week into the office. &lt;em&gt;It just doesn’t make sense any more, especially for freelancers&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;im-thinking-of-leaving-my-full-time-job-now-should-i-do-it&quot;&gt;I’m thinking of leaving my full-time job now! Should I do it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope I wrote quite a comprehensive “guide” in the above paragraphs, although I just reported my personal experience. But let me clear this up: your first answer should be &lt;strong&gt;absolutely not&lt;/strong&gt;, unless:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You really hate being an employee&lt;/strong&gt;. Not just your current or your previous job: you have to look deep inside yourself, and realize you’re not made for this work arrangement of receiving a very safe salary and giving up your 8 hours per day to whatever it’s needed. I mean, it’s not even that different as a daily contractor!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’re financially covered&lt;/strong&gt;. I’d never have made the leap without good savings to cover my arse.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You have one or more certain opportunity ahead&lt;/strong&gt;. Some of your acquaintances (not friends, please!) in need of your skillset, or really any kind of safe project with which to start. Even your previous employer, for a while, if you leave on good terms.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You know what you’re risking&lt;/strong&gt;. Not much to say. As a freelancer, you’re free to empower yourself and earn plenty, as well as shooting yourself in the foot and die crying - financially speaking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-words&quot;&gt;Final words&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I’m pretty happy of this first year:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’ve earned quite well&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’ve worked less&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have a much greater peace of mind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I would do differently:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No need to rush looking for the next opportunity when your yearly revenues are already high: could have taken more time off&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Properly written, arse-covering contracts are more important than I think&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’m not optimistic though. Weird times are coming ahead, with inflation, tech bubble bursting, layoffs, etc.&lt;/strong&gt; Plus, this new life is still a bit new to me; given enough time, I know I could grow wary, and look for another change in the future. Who knows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading so far. I really hope you found some insights in my words. If not, ah, whatever.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Career" /><summary type="html">As you may know, in January 2022 I left my previous full-time employee job as a software engineer, and opened a “partita iva” (VAT number), effectively becoming a proper, self-employed individual.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">About FIRE</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/01/03/about-fire.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="About FIRE" /><published>2023-01-03T07:25:10+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-03T07:25:10+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/01/03/about-fire</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/01/03/about-fire.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I like FIRE&lt;/strong&gt;. I mean, when I read about it in 2015ish, somewhere around Reddit, it seemed like a great idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FIRE: Financial Independence, Retire Early. I’m not going to explain it. If you don’t know what it is about, check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/f/financial-independence-retire-early-fire.asp&quot;&gt;this page from Investopedia&lt;/a&gt; and then come back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There are only some people on Earth capable of pursuing such a dream, and in the end be happy with their choice for a long time&lt;/strong&gt; – until they die, usually.
But most human beings wouldn’t be able to deal with the abnormal consequences FIRE determines. For their lives would suddenly be emptied of certainties, their unspeakable freedom depressingly unenjoyable, since all their friends would be too busy working, spending money and envying them.
Only some rational, lateral-thinking folks are going to seriously try to pursue FIRE; a very small subset of them will achieve it, given how life changes at every turn; but being frugal and smart passive-investors won’t make them good candidates for a complete FIRE life.
&lt;strong&gt;Most of them would probably be better off pursuing some kind of intermediate achievement&lt;/strong&gt;, like amassing enough wealth to pick up a part-time job, and enjoying some more degrees of freedom instead of a full-fledged, totalizing FIRE experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand my statements may sound strong, or even wrong, for some. Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people you and I know have a job. Most people’s jobs are average, with average duties, and average salaries (of course); they usually have an idea of how much they earn, and a very vague notion of their actual spending. These people may save something, but it’s usually just a small nest ready to be depleted with the first vacation, a siny four-wheels, or a new Fabolous-Sized TV. They are bound to their wages. Being this sort of modern slave isn’t too bad after all: it’s culturally acceptable, everybody does the same, and thus very few seriously plan for alternative paths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Now imagine their shock, when somebody, who they thought, after all, was a member of their social group, accepting their same rules and destiny, suddenly breaks free of those shackles&lt;/strong&gt;. Imagine this person coming back from a short interview with HR to pack their stuff. “I’m done, I’m leaving.” “Oh, wow… did you find a better paying job?” “No, I’m done. For good.” “Well… you must have something lined up!” “Nothing’s lined up. Goodbye.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t EXPECTED. This isn’t NORMAL. This isn’t… FAIR. &lt;strong&gt;Congratulations, you’ve suddenly become a pariah&lt;/strong&gt;. A lottery winner, who’s going to lose all their previous friends, their fellow mariners in perilous waters, to take an emergency motorboat to Hawaai.
You’re a danger to the status quo. In evolutionary terms, as “The Elephant In The Brain” cleverly points out, you’re a norm violator. &lt;strong&gt;You just broke the unspoken rule of being a wage slave&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you may lie. You may tell them you found another job, that gives you more “freedom”. They’re going to envy you a bit, but you’re going to stay into their social circle, just a bit farther than their center. But lying won’t help in creating lasting relationships. We’re not wired to lie to our closest peers. And guess what, probably most of your closest peers won’t pursue financial independence, now nor never.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you, &lt;strong&gt;loneliness isn’t for everyone&lt;/strong&gt;. Now imagine: you live a life of frugality and giving up, just to find yourself devoid of friends and people with whom to speak. Is it really desirable? Plus, don’t forget you’re not even in possession of a fat bank account to buy back some of that entertainment. I mean, you have it, but you can’t spend it, otherwise your dream is going to be shattered in a matter of months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not saying you’re doomed to fail, or that nobody at all should pursue FIRE. But well before starting to cut expenses and fill spreadsheets, there should be a solid plan in place. You should probably embark on this journey with someone else – and I’m talking about a friend, a close one, with whom life won’t change after FIRE, apart from seeing him/her more often. I wouldn’t recommend a partner – should something break your relationship, your FIRE plan would probably blow up too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Know your limits as a human being. Don’t underestimate the power of shame, of culture, of being in a society. Your FIRE plan must be sustainable under all aspects:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financially (of course)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Socially&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Psychologically
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I have at least some friends who would totally accept me being unemployed and financially independent, and still frugal?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I have at least a friend who would join me in this journey?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Does my SO understand and accept?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Etc…&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without those basics covered, FIRE is not something I’d pursue, not now, not ever.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Personal finance" /><summary type="html">I like FIRE. I mean, when I read about it in 2015ish, somewhere around Reddit, it seemed like a great idea.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My story - Living the dream, until the Recession hit: 1 to 19 years old</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/my%20story/2022/10/14/my-personal-story-part-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My story - Living the dream, until the Recession hit: 1 to 19 years old" /><published>2022-10-14T12:42:56+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-14T12:42:56+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/my%20story/2022/10/14/my-personal-story-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/my%20story/2022/10/14/my-personal-story-part-1.html">&lt;p&gt;My story starts in the 90s, in a town in central Italy, not too far from the seaside, in a beautiful landscape of hills and historical remembrances, but also a pretty dynamic industrial hub.
The town I was born in was, and still is, an average sized town for Italy, of around 40 thousand inhabitants.
The first neighbourhood I have fond memories of, is a pretty green, well-served place not too far from the city centre. Lots of families, and friends around my age to play football (soccer!) with. Life was great.
I was born in a higher-middle class family, both traditional and liberal, so to say. My father worked as an entrepreneur, while my mother had a more classic 9-to-5 job.
My parents did pretty well overall. The 90s in Italy were probably the last decade of “wellbeing” for our economy, although not even close to the roaring growth we experienced in the 60s, 70s and 80s.
I was educated as a proper catholic, and even served as an altar boy for some years, with our local community. I only have good memories of the two priests who managed that church, and I’m a bit sad that I’ve lost my faith over the years – I can define myself as an agnostic individual, towards faiths in general.
Anyway, I attended primary school both mornings and afternoons, apart from Wednesdays and Saturdays (and of course Sundays we were free!). Since my parents had a pretty busy working life, I spent a lot of time with my grandma.
Of course, there would be a lot to write about, but I think it’d end up boring you, my reader. Nice memories for myself, good for a diary maybe, but not a public blog.
The most interesting part to highlight is probably my family’s finances. As I said, my parents were in pretty good shape. We had a nice apartment, went for some vacations abroad every year (which I hated… sorry, that’s how I am), and I had access to PCs, consoles, bikes, and so on. I think my father was leaning towards saving money most of the time, and my mother sometimes argued with him about that, but not in front of us kids.
I was given a weekly allowance of 10 thousand lire, which is the equivalent, in today’s money, of roughly 10 euros. I spent all of it, each time. Saving for something wasn’t in my mind, and although my father tried to teach me, for some reason it didn’t stick. At the times, I was a &lt;i&gt;spendaccione&lt;i&gt;, rather than a money saver.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Italy, the 2000s eras began with some historical changes. In 2002, starting January 1st, the Euro currency suddenly appeared. I remember being at a &lt;i&gt;tabaccaio&lt;i&gt; (a common shop in Italy, selling tobacco, stamps, lottery tickets and so on), and being given these weird coins as change for my lire… and being a bit puzzled about their appearance.
In my personal life, I graduated from primary school (there was a sort of exam at the time, now I think they just deleted it) and went to scuola media (middle school).
During these times, I started to change a bit. An ADSL, meaning “broadband internet”, was installed in our home. I started playing videogames in a more intense manner than before, and playing online with strangers became my thing. My parents became increasingly worried, for good reasons, and started fighting my addiction for video games, limiting my time I had access to the PC.
The Italian economy kept growing, as well as house prices. &lt;i&gt;Investi nel mattone&lt;i&gt; (“Invest into real estate”) was the motto of every living adult in Italy. Stocks plummeted in 2000-2001, while houses were still greatly priced! What could go wrong, if you had a nice set of bricks instead of volatile financial products in your pockets?
Anyway, my world, already endangered, fell apart completely from 2008. People started talking about this “crisis”, this “recession” thing. Strange, scary words we had never heard before, in our blind wellbeing over the years. My father worked in a pretty exposed field (yes… houses), and had just taken huge loans for a &lt;i&gt;monstre&lt;i&gt; project, which would have made us rich, prosperous, step up in the Olympus! … and actually, brought only troubles.
Things went south quickly. The Italian financial markets turned out to be inflated (a lot!), in a gigantic bubble which popped silently at first, and then devastated our country as months passed by. It was like watching a nuclear explosion from space, and then realizing you were actually too close to it. You may all know the effect of a recession, but what you may have not experienced, is the feeling of a crisis which still hasn’t passed, still looming, alongside fear and regrets. To put it into perspective, while the S&amp;amp;P 500 recovered historical highs and doubled it, our index, the Italian FTSE MIB, is still 50% lower than the 2007 peak. Of course, our index is not a total return one, (meaning, a stock index in which dividends are accounted for). Our equivalent, the FTSE MIB TR, has only very recently reached the 2007 peak, and is already going down these weeks.
In 2009, after graduating from high school, I decided I had enough of my life and town so far, and took off, thanks to some savings my father had accumulated through the years. I went to Bologna’s university, one of the most well known in Italy, and started my academic life there. More about it in the next post of the series.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="My story" /><summary type="html">My story starts in the 90s, in a town in central Italy, not too far from the seaside, in a beautiful landscape of hills and historical remembrances, but also a pretty dynamic industrial hub. The town I was born in was, and still is, an average sized town for Italy, of around 40 thousand inhabitants. The first neighbourhood I have fond memories of, is a pretty green, well-served place not too far from the city centre. Lots of families, and friends around my age to play football (soccer!) with. Life was great. I was born in a higher-middle class family, both traditional and liberal, so to say. My father worked as an entrepreneur, while my mother had a more classic 9-to-5 job. My parents did pretty well overall. The 90s in Italy were probably the last decade of “wellbeing” for our economy, although not even close to the roaring growth we experienced in the 60s, 70s and 80s. I was educated as a proper catholic, and even served as an altar boy for some years, with our local community. I only have good memories of the two priests who managed that church, and I’m a bit sad that I’ve lost my faith over the years – I can define myself as an agnostic individual, towards faiths in general. Anyway, I attended primary school both mornings and afternoons, apart from Wednesdays and Saturdays (and of course Sundays we were free!). Since my parents had a pretty busy working life, I spent a lot of time with my grandma. Of course, there would be a lot to write about, but I think it’d end up boring you, my reader. Nice memories for myself, good for a diary maybe, but not a public blog. The most interesting part to highlight is probably my family’s finances. As I said, my parents were in pretty good shape. We had a nice apartment, went for some vacations abroad every year (which I hated… sorry, that’s how I am), and I had access to PCs, consoles, bikes, and so on. I think my father was leaning towards saving money most of the time, and my mother sometimes argued with him about that, but not in front of us kids. I was given a weekly allowance of 10 thousand lire, which is the equivalent, in today’s money, of roughly 10 euros. I spent all of it, each time. Saving for something wasn’t in my mind, and although my father tried to teach me, for some reason it didn’t stick. At the times, I was a spendaccione, rather than a money saver.</summary></entry></feed>