<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-05T18:54:42+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">NaNDay.dev Blog</title><subtitle>Life, thoughts, software engineering.</subtitle><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><entry><title type="html">Travelling is nice, but it won’t make you a better human being</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/thoughts/2025/01/05/i-dont-like-travelling-part-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Travelling is nice, but it won’t make you a better human being" /><published>2025-01-05T18:05:46+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-05T18:05:46+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/thoughts/2025/01/05/i-dont-like-travelling-part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/thoughts/2025/01/05/i-dont-like-travelling-part-2.html"><![CDATA[<p>Ok, after 6 posts about TTRPGs (yeah, I know, enough for now), let’s go back to an evergreen of my grumblings. <strong>Traveling!</strong></p>

<p>Just today, I read <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ItaliaPersonalFinance/comments/1hu8kyi/i_viaggi_sono_inutili/">a post on Italia Personal Finance</a> (Italian only, sorry) about travelling.</p>

<p>To sum it up: OP is whining about his friends all spending 2k / 3k € every year for a trip outside EU, and his girlfriend pushing him to do the same for them, while he’d rather spend much less and not go that far.</p>

<p>If you have already read <a href="/blog/thoughts/2023/01/09/i-dont-like-travelling.html">my other post about travelling</a>, you may think I 100% agree with OP, proudly nodded while staring at my screen, and even gave him a solid, bright upvote.</p>

<p>Nah.</p>

<p>First of all, going into Reddit to whine this much sounds as mature as a green orange.</p>

<p>Apart from that, as I wrote in that original post, I think it should be a <strong>personal</strong> choice. It’s called <em>personal</em> finance for a reason after all.</p>

<p>So, maybe OP’s girlfiend finds joy and excitement traveling every year to a different place, for 2 or 3 weeks. I’d rather hang myself to the ceiling with a rope, singing a Taylor Swift’s song. OP is probably fine with just some travel around Europe here and there.</p>

<p>If we agree nothing’s wrong in each of us, there’s another point I’d like to address.</p>

<p>A lot of people in the comments wrote something along the line of <em>“But OP, traveling OPENS YOUR MIND.”</em>.
Now, let me vehemently disagree for a minute here.</p>

<p>If you need traveling to open your mind, with all the burden it brings, the financial costs, etc., I have bad news for you.</p>

<p>I don’t travel a lot, or, almost never, in the common sense of boarding on a plane and going far away with a backpack on the shoulders and a big smile on my face. I go away on weekends, yes, but mostly driving with my significant other somewhere within 2 to 4 hours around here. By the way, I assure you you’ll find unending new, interesting places around your hometown, especially if you live in Italy. But that’s topic for another post.</p>

<p>But, lo and behold, I consider myself quite open-minded. Yeah, I mean, almost nobody would tell you <em>“I’m CLOSE-MINDED and proud of it!”</em>. But I rarely find myself judging in a superficial way. I like philosophy, literature (I almost graduated in Italian modern literature, after all). Almost all my friends consider me an interesting, lateral-thinking person.</p>

<p>I mean, maybe back in the 50s, somebody traveling more than the others could proudly call themself “more open-minded”. Today, the ready availability of information, different cultures and opinions on the internet, makes that argument sound silly, in my opinion.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, since love for travel is so widespread, people tend to generalize their overwhelming joy of sleeping in a cramped, dusty hotel. Your humble opinion of “I don’t like traveling, sorry, but good for you if you do!” usually sounds to them something along the line of “I decapitate kittens to have a better sleep”.</p>

<p>I know, I sound bitter. It’s a bit painful after all, hating travel, in a world of travel enthusiasts. Hope you’ll forgive me.</p>

<p>Until next time!</p>]]></content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Thoughts" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ok, after 6 posts about TTRPGs (yeah, I know, enough for now), let’s go back to an evergreen of my grumblings. Traveling!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Obsidian, or how technology helps my games</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/tabletop%20role-playing%20games/2024/12/20/obsidian-how-technology-helps-my-games.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Obsidian, or how technology helps my games" /><published>2024-12-20T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-20T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/tabletop%20role-playing%20games/2024/12/20/obsidian-how-technology-helps-my-games</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/tabletop%20role-playing%20games/2024/12/20/obsidian-how-technology-helps-my-games.html"><![CDATA[<p>As you may or may not know, I call myself a software engineer. Others call me a software engineer. So, I guess that’s what I am, professionally speaking.</p>

<p>Even though there are some software engineers out there who refuse to touch any PC or do any coding outside their working hours, I’ve never really been like that. Even when I was putting insane amount of hours into a gigantic product which never saw the light because corporate, back in 2019, I still had the spark in me to write some hobby code when I was back at home. If I did it less in that period, was not because I was lacking the will of writing some more code outside my work hours: it was just a matter of time.</p>

<p>So, it is sort of natural to let technology flow into my game preparations, and sessions themselves, for the purpose of enhancing the overall experience both for me and my players.</p>

<p>The first thing we’re going to talk about, hopefully in this first post of many others of a series, is Obsidian.</p>

<p>Obsidian belongs, as far as I understand, to a whole category of “note-taking” software. But that would be grossly understating its potential actually. Obsidian, similar to Notion and others, is actually about building your digital, inter-connected brain of text, images and other documents.</p>

<p>The first reason I found it was because, when building my setting, lot of times I’ll need to change a name I had decided. I’m not good with inventing names, and sometimes, following the flow of an idea, I just write something I made up in that moment. I don’t really like placeholders: re-reading the document would be too hard. So, almost always, when I go back to read that part, I inevitably cringe at the name I had given beforehand. But that name had spread at that moment; maybe I even wrote another document with that name, to take some notes on the character/place/event.</p>

<p>Let’s say for instance I’m writing about the “Great Pacts of Mount Thoradin”, which ended the war between human, dwarves and elves in my world. I know who the elven leader is, since she’s millennia years old: Elora The Venerable, of course. But dwarves, and humans even more, have shorter lifespans. So, as a temporary dwarf “king” (dwarves have no single leader: arguing and quarreling between themselves would be too hard), I’m going to write the name Ulfbar. And I’m also going to create a note for Ulfbar: another file, named “Ulfbar.docx”, in which I’ll write maybe a couple of lines to remember why his name is there.</p>

<p>But then, re-reading that part, the name “Ulfbar” really sounds more like the dog of a dwarven king, not really the king himself. So I’d need to change it, possibly quickly.</p>

<p>Microsoft Word is ok, but when I tried a couple of ways to have this “table of names” which would be easily editable, it failed. There’s probably a better way, but I gave up. Please, searching among documents… too clunky.</p>

<p>So I made a bit of research, and found Obsidian. It’s perfect for my needs: it generates Markdown files, which are just plain text files (just like .txt), and when you put names in this two square brackets [[Ulfbar]], it creates a link. You can then use the same link elsewhere, and when you’re ready, create the Ulfbar page. If you decide Ulfbar is a horrible name, you just need to rename the Ulfbar file inside Obsidian: it will automatically update all files mentioning Ulfbar (provided you used the link in those files, and not the plain name).</p>

<p>Plus, it’s free. Only paid features you may want, are cloud backups and syncs. Since I know pretty well Git (a source control software, mainly used for code), I didn’t really need it: I’m using the Git Obsidian plugin, and syncing all my files to a free Github account.</p>

<p>The downside is, though, I can’t really access my files while on mobile. I still have to search for a workaround though, I’m sure it’s doable with a little hack.</p>

<p>With Obsidian, I can now proudly say I crossed over 1000 files in my homemade setting for D&amp;D, and I don’t know how many lines. There are also a lot of empty files, of course, which I just created so that one day I’ll write them (maybe). But the Obsidian search is still blazingly fast, and also opening the software doesn’t take more than a second. Even on my older laptop.</p>

<p>There are some things I’d like improved, and probably there are plugins for that. For instance, I don’t always want to use the full name of something or someone in files, especially when I’m repeating it more than once. For instance, Kelton The Red, leader of the Scarlet Phalanx, mercenaries with anarchic-good tendencies, is better shortened as “Kelton”. There’s the possibility, in Obsidian, to create “aliases” for files. But then, when I edit an alias, other files are not actually updated, because aliases are just suggestions for auto-completion, not indexed as file names are.</p>

<p>But overall, Obsidian 9/10. No better way to prepare sessions and create your world.</p>

<p>In the next episode, I’ll likely talk about Owlbear Rodeo, or maybe one of my own software creations. We’ll see.</p>

<p>Thanks for reading, and until next time.</p>]]></content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Tabletop Role-Playing Games" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As you may or may not know, I call myself a software engineer. Others call me a software engineer. So, I guess that’s what I am, professionally speaking.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tips for finding a date for your sessions</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/tabletop%20role-playing%20games/2024/12/13/tips-for-finding-a-date-for-your-sessions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tips for finding a date for your sessions" /><published>2024-12-13T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-13T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/tabletop%20role-playing%20games/2024/12/13/tips-for-finding-a-date-for-your-sessions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/tabletop%20role-playing%20games/2024/12/13/tips-for-finding-a-date-for-your-sessions.html"><![CDATA[<p>You may be one of lucky few who don’t struggle too much to find a date for your TTRPG sessions among your players.</p>

<p>Maybe you all go to the same office and can just stay for dinner there, and have fun later. (Is it still a thing in 2024?)</p>

<p>Maybe you just have a weekday where everybody knows there will be D&amp;D, everybody is free and happy and nothing goes wrong.</p>

<p>Or maybe you’re young and brave as I was when I had half my age, and just have endless time at your complete disposal to play together, just whenever.</p>

<p>My experience is wildly different. I struggle almost every week to have everyone at the table playing, just for an evening. Life’s busy. People are busy.</p>

<p>With one group, we also have worse difficulties, since, while somebody has “normal” (?) 9-5 jobs, somebody else may work until 8 pm, and somebody else even works only between 7 and 10 pm. It’s a complete mess.</p>

<p>At first, I was a little happy naive DM. Every week, we would have session, and then, while leaving the building around midnight, we’d tell each other “Let’s chat on WhatsApp and plan the next one!”.</p>

<p>Critical mistake.</p>

<p>I’d spend the next days juggling between the players’ commitments, just like their personal non-AI assistant, to try to find a slot for our session.</p>

<p>I was miserable. But I thought it was the thing a DM had to do. So I did it. Very manly, wow.</p>

<p>Then I looked at all the other things I do as a DM. Prepping. Writing previous session’s summary. Re-reading player character’s background stories. Etc etc.</p>

<p>And one day I sort of gave up. I gathered all the player’s weekly commitments, put them on a table. And it was obvious there would be no time slot ideal for everybody. It wasn’t only “I can’t be there on Sunday’s evening”: somebody also had the audacity to say “I’d rather not play on Sunday, I have to wake up early on Monday”.</p>

<p>(Joking, of course. It’s totally understandable.)</p>

<p>So, we had a good talk, and I straight up told them: “We can’t make everybody happy. There’s zero possibility. We need to make somebody unhappy each time, maybe just once a month for each of you.”</p>

<p>And I presented them with a schedule! A magnificent, planned schedule of all sessions ahead, from September to December. Each week, we’d hurt (not phisically) a single player, and, if possible, we’d cross not their commitments, but the days they’d rather not play. Such as the dreaded Sunday evening above.</p>

<p>Did it work? Sort of. Some commitments changed, and we had to make adjustments on the way. But having a schedule of all sessions helped tremendously. They already knew in which date they’d be busy with D&amp;D, so suddenly, instead of sessions having to juggle between players’ schedule, it was other commitments’ juggling between sessions (if priority was same or lower, of course).</p>

<p>So, if just like me, you struggle with planning session dates, here’s my advice:</p>

<p>Make a schedule. Do it weeks, or even months, ahead.</p>

<p>If there’s not a perfect fit for everybody, arrange dates so that somebody “gives up” every time, rotating between players’ commitments.</p>

<p>If a player suddenly has an issue with a pre-agreed date, it’s their responsibility, not yours, to contact everybody and try to find a different date. Otherwise, the date doesn’t change. It’s a matter of mental health. Yours.</p>]]></content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Tabletop Role-Playing Games" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You may be one of lucky few who don’t struggle too much to find a date for your TTRPG sessions among your players.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Players using AI to write their own character’s story</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/tabletop%20role-playing%20games/2024/12/04/players-using-ai-to-write-their-characters-story.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Players using AI to write their own character’s story" /><published>2024-12-04T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-04T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/tabletop%20role-playing%20games/2024/12/04/players-using-ai-to-write-their-characters-story</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/tabletop%20role-playing%20games/2024/12/04/players-using-ai-to-write-their-characters-story.html"><![CDATA[<p>Even though I live in one of the most slow countries of EU, in terms of “receptiviness to technology”, ChatGPT and the other generative “AIs” finally made an appearance at my table.</p>

<p>I just started another campaign, while my main one is still going strong, with some friends. During “session zero”, I introduced the good old homework every player must to do, before starting: writing a backstory, a background, a story for their character. Call it whatever you like: just some phrases about who they are, where they’re from, etc.</p>

<p>Until now, people on average sent me very unreadable messes, if they ever sent me something. Sometimes, I told them to just produce a list of highlights from their character’s past, and I’d write the “fictionalized” version for them. After writing about 4 or 5, though, I stopped. It was fun, but too much work.</p>

<p>Now, two new players surprisingly told me they’d use ChatGPT. It was kind of obvious for them. I didn’t object. I mean, my opinion about ChatGPT, in terms of creative writing, is the same any amateur or better writer will tell you: mediocre. Mediocre, in the sense of I’d give its outputs a 6 out of 10 probably, if I felt particularly generous.</p>

<p>But what I’d usually rate my player’s backgrounds, when written by themselves, is a solid 3. Sometimes less. I don’t know about you, but, for real, my players’ writing skills are abismal. Apart from one who wanted to become a writer, all the others just can’t sit down and express themselves with a decent paragraph. Some of them don’t even own a PC, so they just write something with their smartphone, which I must admit is a frustrating experience at best, and then send me a screenshot of their phone. I die inside a little when I receive those.</p>

<p>I’m not saying I’m a good writer, by any mean. My main language is Italian, also, so you may find mistakes here and there in my writing. But maybe, just maybe, we’re all becoming increasingly incapable of writing, on average. Or maybe I’m just very unlucky.</p>

<p>But I digress. Some days after session zero, players sent me their ChatGPT-written backgrounds. And… they weren’t too bad, especially because they edited a couple of details to fit in my setting. Nothing extraordinary, of course. But far, far better than what I usually have to read. At least, there were finer details, even though nothing great or very inspiring. Something I can build on.</p>

<p>I have a private website for my players, with the collection of characters, NPCs, session summaries. And their character’s background story. I used to refuse to upload what they usually sent me, and sometimes, when I received screenshots instead of text, I’d have to rewrite them anyway. So, I guess with ChatGPT I won’t have to do it any more, and can just upload them as they are, more or less.</p>

<p>A small improvement for me, a big loss for humanity.</p>

<p>Not that there was much left to save, in the first place.</p>]]></content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Tabletop Role-Playing Games" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Even though I live in one of the most slow countries of EU, in terms of “receptiviness to technology”, ChatGPT and the other generative “AIs” finally made an appearance at my table.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Taking premade adventures and making them your own</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/tabletop%20role-playing%20games/2024/11/07/taking-premade-adventures-and-making-them-your-own.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Taking premade adventures and making them your own" /><published>2024-11-07T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-07T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/tabletop%20role-playing%20games/2024/11/07/taking-premade-adventures-and-making-them-your-own</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/tabletop%20role-playing%20games/2024/11/07/taking-premade-adventures-and-making-them-your-own.html"><![CDATA[<p>As we’re nearing the end of the first narrative arc of my campaign, with the incoming battle with Explictica Defilus this next Sunday (I’m quite proud of the encounter I’ve prepared!), one thing came up while exploring the dungeon just before the naga’s lair.</p>

<p><strong>For those of you who have never heard the name, I’m talking about the AD&amp;D module Against the Cult of the Reptile God</strong>, which is a really neat product from the 80s, and you should give it a try as a DM.</p>

<p>Anyway. I didn’t really like the idea of Explictica Defilus living in the “basement” of a muddy, wet dungeon in the middle of a swamp. It’s a powerful spiritual naga we’re talking about! She must have witnessed countless civilizations come and go within centuries, or even millennia! That’s not a decent place for her lair. At the same time, I also wanted to try out one of the adventures inside Tales from the Yawning Portal, that my friends (not from my table, other friends) gifted me on my birthday (but funnily enough, I only received the book about 5 months later… long story).</p>

<p><strong>So, I gave it a quick read, and decided my Explictica Defilus would be living inside the ziggurat from The Hidden Shrine of Tamoachan</strong>, an AD&amp;D adventure brought to 5e. What are you saying? It’s because it’s the only adventure fit for my PCs level? Maybe. Maybe.</p>

<p>Thing is, until now, I didn’t have a real plan for Explictica, and made NPCs throughout the adventure describe her lair as an “underground lake”, as it should have been in the original module. But now, if you read The Hidden Shrine of Tamoachan, you’ll notice the adventure actually starts in the underground, and ends up in the top level of the ziggurat. Oopsie.</p>

<p>So, I just decided that, on top of the ziggurat, the player would find a portal for the underground lair. It’s the only access to the lair, as far as they know, or at least, it’s the one Explictica’s cultists use.</p>

<p><strong>But the thing is, if a “normal” underground dungeon, such as the one in the original module of the Reptile God, made perfectly sense, and after all, not too much explanation was needed for it (caverns with water underground, duh) … having a full ziggurat out of nowhere, in the middle of a swamp, is a bit harder to digest.</strong></p>

<p>I’m lucky, in the sense that the whole setting is homebrewed by myself, so I can have some freedom that a random Forgotten Realms or Greyhawk probably wouldn’t give me. The whole ziggurat thing actually gave me very decent ideas about one missing part of my setting: where did humans come from?</p>

<p>What I had written before, was that they sort of appeared by the end of the “Dwarven” era, and, united as one great tribe, battled the dwarves, who were too proud and split between different nations. Humans, led by the first king Martin I, won, made peace with the dwarves and the elves, and founded the Great Human Kingdom.</p>

<p>But now, having that ziggurat, and all those ancient human gods, made me rethink the actual origin of the human species. I also thought about one of the things I most like about the Kult RPG: the idea that human beings are actually all gods, who forgot their divine nature, and are trapped in the cage of reality, where their godhood is so well hidden that they think of themselves as mere mortals without any power.</p>

<p>The Tamoachan tribe was, nontheless, a primitive tribe. They had no spark of divinity in themselves. But, ancient as they were, they actually remembered those even more ancient times. The tale of their ancestors, living gods and goddesses in a city embalmed in bright light, up the highest mountain range of the whole continent, is still vivid in their imagination. They know their ancestors were gods, and lost everything, when one of them decided to pick up from the ground a red fragment, probably of a meteorite, and waged war against the elves and the ancient dragons…</p>

<p>Anyway, enough with the story I imagined. The lesson here, I guess, is you can take anything you like, from books, movies, other adventures, and not only adapt it to yours, but even grab those things you like of it, and use them to fill gaps into your world.</p>

<p>Back to our campaign, players started exploring the ziggurat. It took about 3 sessions overall. Actually, I decided to skip the upper two levels. Why? Things were taking too long: too big of a dungeon, too many things to see, I was getting bored.</p>

<p>Also, since I put that subtitle on this article, I have to explain: at one point of the dungeon, there’s a boulder blocking the way. The PCs, joining forces, can move it a little, letting one or two of them pass. What happened is, of course, the group split. At the end of the session, they were still splitted, and one of the group wanted to sleep for 8 hours, because they had their spells depleted to survive. But the other group was just a couple of rooms away at that point: instead of letting them stay this way, and make separate sessions… and who knows what… I just told them they’d instead join with the first group first, and then rest. Yeah, a bit metagam-ish, but totally avoided some headaches for me and them.</p>

<p>Anyway. The top of the Tamochoan dungeon in the original module is actually not so interesting, treasure apart. So I decided that’d be the place where the players would fight against THOKXOT, CULT’S VANGUARD! It’s an enemy NPC I totally invented, not in the original Reptile God module. And it’s also a dear enemy of my players: it actually almost TPK’ed (= total player kill, AKA party wipeout) all of them, some sessions ago. Only the warlock and the sorcerer made it back alive, thanks to Invisibility and my uttermost graceful heart.</p>

<p>The roof of the ziggurat was a perfect place for an ambush to the PCs. But I gave them the chance to solve a puzzle, at the end of the ziggurat, and if they did solve it, they would have found a way to avoid the ambush, and actually ambush Thokxot and his guards themselves. Which they did!</p>

<p>With them, there was Ramne, an old wizard (which I think is also in the original module). He told the PCs, just before the fight, that there’s a portal to Explictica Defilus’ lair on the roof. It’s on an altar, between the arms of a statue of a fallen angel (an angel with the wings turned into bones, representing the fall of the divinity within humans).</p>

<p>He told them he’d be busy trying to seal the portal, while they had to defend him and kill Thokxot. Not an easy task.</p>

<p>It was an epic fight! And the funny thing is, as soon as Ramne sealed the portal, he invoked a greater demon to fight amongside them. Of course, what happened is the demon got free of Ramne’s enchantment on the first turn, and started attacking the players. The barbarian/druid decided to enter into rage, jumped on the demon, and started to bite it. At the same time though, the demon was dismissed back into the Abyss (takes 1d6 turn after you lose control of it). The barbarian almost ended up teleported into the Abyss with the demon. Fortunately for him, Ramne managed to teleport him away just in time!</p>

<p>Next session, they’ll reopen the portal again, and enter a new realm of madness. We’ll see how they manage.</p>

<p>I hope reading this new post was fun, let me know your opinions in the comment section below, if you wish!</p>

<p>Until next time.</p>]]></content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Tabletop Role-Playing Games" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As we’re nearing the end of the first narrative arc of my campaign, with the incoming battle with Explictica Defilus this next Sunday (I’m quite proud of the encounter I’ve prepared!), one thing came up while exploring the dungeon just before the naga’s lair.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I wrote a D&amp;amp;D Combat Management App</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/tabletop%20role-playing%20games/2024/10/28/i-wrote-a-dnd-combat-management-app.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I wrote a D&amp;amp;D Combat Management App" /><published>2024-10-28T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-28T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/tabletop%20role-playing%20games/2024/10/28/i-wrote-a-dnd-combat-management-app</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/tabletop%20role-playing%20games/2024/10/28/i-wrote-a-dnd-combat-management-app.html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="humble-beginnings">Humble beginnings</h3>

<p>So, this weekend my SO went to visit her parents in Rome.</p>

<p>I was home alone, and apart from our campaign’s session on Saturday, barbecue-dinner with my friends and players, and a brief walk on Sunday, I didn’t have much to do.</p>

<p>One thing you should know is I’m a freelance software engineer, specialized in mobile apps. But I enjoy doing some backend here and there, and even desktop apps sometimes.</p>

<p>So, after the session, I started thinking about ways to improve the flow of certain things we do while playing D&amp;D.</p>

<p>One of the pain points is spell descriptions and properties. I sort of fixed that, imposing players to print their own spell cards, and we’ll probably do the same with abilities, talents, etc. I also have, on my laptop’s Obsidian app (where I keep all the session notes while playing), all the descriptions of the spell. So, when the need arises, I can just press Ctrl + O, search “Magic missile” and open the spell description. I’d rather players do it though, already too much to think about during a fight. That’s why… cards.</p>

<p>Another pain point is, in my opinion, combat. Fights. I tried using Owlbear Rodeo for initiative, but I didn’t find it useful enough. For those of you who don’t know, it’s a virtual “tabletop” simulator, very barebone, but just about right for my sessions. We use a projector during fights to show everybody Owlbear Rodeo, the grid and the miniatures, and it works perfectly for us.</p>

<p>But the way initiative is implemented in OR? Nah. I didn’t like it.</p>

<p>So, what does a good software engineer do in these cases? Spend 10 minutes searching for a good alternative on the internet, and use it next time? Or spend the entire Sunday, morning to late night, rolling their own solution for the problem, from scratch?</p>

<p>Yeah, that’s what I did. Look, it’s not the rational thing to do. I bet there are hundreds of combat management apps for D&amp;D online, much better than mine, with more features, better UI, better UX. Maybe even without bugs.</p>

<p>But I don’t care. I just wanted to write my own, have it my way. Learn a thing or two, which I always do, when I embark in these projects.</p>

<p>Plus, I don’t get much uninterrumpted focus time on my work, almost ever, these days. Once you reach a level of seniority in the team, people won’t just leave you alone. Not complaining though. I mean, yeah I’m complaining a bit. OK, I’m complaining a lot. I’m whining about it. But I really enjoy when I can sit down, with a good cup of hot tea, and just start hurting my keyboard like hell for hours.</p>

<p>But enough talking. Here it is.</p>

<p><img src="/blog/assets/images/dnd-combat-management-app-preview.webp" alt="First draft of my D&amp;D Combat Management App" /></p>

<p>First column is, simply put, the list of all combatants in the current fight. As you can see, some are editable (NPCs, monsters), others are fixed (PCs). That’s because player characters are inserted at the application’s first setup (more below), and it wouldn’t make much sense to change their names each fight.</p>

<p>Second column is the initative. One nice thing I did, that I don’t usually find elsewhere, is changing the initiative automatically sorts the list, without any other button to press.</p>

<p>Then there are turns: an empty slot means the turn hasn’t started yet; a cross means the turn is over; the hourglass means the character chose to delay their turn. I didn’t put an “in progress” sign, since I didn’t find it useful: it’s usually quite obvious whose’s turn it is at the moment (and yes, it’s always that player’s turn, who ponders for hours before picking… the wrong action).</p>

<p>After that, there are health points. But only for non player characters. I trust my player to track their own health points!</p>

<p>The “minus” button serves the scope of just inserting how much you wish to subtract from the current health points. Especially useful at higher levels. So for instance, if you press the HP (or current hp score, if you’ve already inserted it), you can directly set the current health points:</p>

<p><img src="/blog/assets/images/dnd-combat-management-app-preview-2.webp" alt="D&amp;D Combat Management App" /></p>

<p>Otherwise, you can press the minus, either on the table or here, to subtract from the 560:</p>

<p><img src="/blog/assets/images/dnd-combat-management-app-preview-3.webp" alt="D&amp;D Combat Management App" /></p>

<p>Longest dialog title of the Milky Way, probably.</p>

<p>Then press “OK”, and the table gets updated.</p>

<p>Finally, the “notes” column, for any notes to be taken, such as “Has disadvantage on hit”, etc. Those notes, for players, are also saved to disk, so that you don’t have to remember each player’s current condition or bonus between fights.</p>

<p>But, let’s see the least interesting part. At the application startup, you can insert your campaign, and all the player characters.</p>

<p><img src="/blog/assets/images/dnd-combat-management-app-preview-4.webp" alt="D&amp;D Combat Management App" /></p>

<p>Also, why not, create new campaigns with different PCs.</p>

<p><img src="/blog/assets/images/dnd-combat-management-app-preview-5.webp" alt="D&amp;D Combat Management App" /></p>

<p><img src="/blog/assets/images/dnd-combat-management-app-preview-6.webp" alt="D&amp;D Combat Management App" /></p>

<p>and then switch to the Fight! tab and create a combat.</p>

<p><img src="/blog/assets/images/dnd-combat-management-app-preview-7.webp" alt="D&amp;D Combat Management App" /></p>

<p><img src="/blog/assets/images/dnd-combat-management-app-preview-8.webp" alt="D&amp;D Combat Management App" /></p>

<p>Yeah, UI and UX are not great, I’m just a software engineer. Designing things is a bit too much for me, especially when I’m just making a hobby project such as this.</p>

<p>For colleagues: I used Flutter/Dart, and at the moment it’s only compatible with Windows, but it can easily be deployed to almost any native platform. Although I’d have to probably rework something about the table for mobile, unless I’m forcing the user to use it landscape.</p>

<p>Deploying it to a web page should technically work. But I’d have to see how I can access some persistent storage, probably cookies wouldn’t be persistent enough!</p>

<p>Anyway, that’s it. I’ll let you know this weekend, as soon as I have the chance to try it out. Maybe one day I’ll publish it. Not for free, HEHEHEHE. Ok, maybe free with a donation.</p>

<p>Should you have any question, suggestion, rant, whatever, please write in the comments below.</p>

<p>Until next time folks!</p>]]></content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Tabletop Role-Playing Games" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Humble beginnings]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My history with TTRPGs</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/tabletop%20role-playing%20games/2024/10/26/my-history-with-ttrpgs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My history with TTRPGs" /><published>2024-10-26T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-26T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/tabletop%20role-playing%20games/2024/10/26/my-history-with-ttrpgs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/tabletop%20role-playing%20games/2024/10/26/my-history-with-ttrpgs.html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="humble-beginnings">Humble beginnings</h3>

<p>I’ve been playing TTRPGs for quite some years. Can’t remember the exact year, but D&amp;D 3.0 had just came out, so I guess it was 2000 or so.</p>

<p>It all started in summer break. Here in Italy, there’s only one gigantic vacation during the school year (apart from some days off here and there, due to national festivities), and it lasts 3 months: mid-June to mid-September. So, my parents had to scramble to find a way to fill my days with something, and have somebody watch me over, I guess.</p>

<p>That year, they heard a travel agency was taking all kids together, for a couple of weeks, and bringing them to a remote place in the middle of nowhere in central Italy, nearby a mountain lake, in a big hotel. There, they would attend English lessons with native teachers, and also play sports, swim, etc.</p>

<p>Having my kids out of my house for 2 whole weeks, day and night, plus them learning English? SIGN ME UP! No, wait, sign THEM up! my parents must have thought, and that’s how I ended up in “Parco del Lago” (= Lake Park) hotel in July, with a bunch of other pre-teenagers from all around Italy.</p>

<p>I went twice to those experiences, and my feelings now are… mixed, especially on that first time I went. But one good thing came out of it: I was introduced to D&amp;D by a group of nerdy kids there!</p>

<p>We played this kind of extremely barebone 3.0 ruleset, where you only had to get a 16 on the d20 dice to hit monsters, no matter your class, abilities or whatever, no roleplaying at all, just dungeon crawling and boss fights. The DM had a PC-NPC he nurtured like a baby bird (I can still remember the name: Salomon), and the last time I played during that vacation, was when we fought a minotaur boss. We got lucky with dices, defeated it quickly, and, in the cheering, I dared say loud: “Oh wow, that was easy!”. The DM of course took it as a personal offense, resurrected the minotaur, and proceeded to kill my best (for the vacation) friend’s PC. Of course, that same friend blamed me for it. Since I strongly disagreed, we didn’t make peace before departing. Oh well.</p>

<p>In the hotel, there was also another D&amp;D group, which was playing more by the rules. I was talking to the DM once, who told me he regretted giving his players too many magic items. So, I suggested «Hey, why don’t you make them end up in the middle of some lake, or sea, and sink their ship, so they have to drop those armors and weapons to survive?». I guess I already had the little (bastard) soul of a DM in myself.</p>

<p>Ah, good times.</p>

<p>Anyway, after that experience, I came back home and told my parents «I WANT TO PLAY D&amp;D!», and they dutifully went to the library and bought… the DM’s guide. Nice, but not the first thing I needed.</p>

<p>I bought the PHB some times after, and even the monsters’ manual. Thing is, I didn’t find a group to play with, in my hometown. And I was too introverted to propose it to anyone. So, for a while, those books just sit there, taking some dust.</p>

<h3 id="resurrection-of-the-hobby">Resurrection of the hobby</h3>

<p>But around 2005 or so, as I was in high school, I heard a couple of my classmates talk about mages and spells. My eyes went wide. It was D&amp;D! Dungeons &amp; Freakin’ Dragons! Took some courage… a lot of courage, actually… did I already mention I’m introverted?… and went to them, asking to join the group!</p>

<p>They sort of agreed to let me in. Couple of days later, we met with the others, and started playing. D&amp;D 3.5 had came out, so my manuals were outdated, and being a poor-as-a-teenager teenager, I didn’t buy any more. Our DM had them, and I guess it was enough. No setting books, no adventure books, nothing. Just the good old 3 PHB, DMG and MM. A lot of imagination, and most of all, plenty of time.</p>

<p>Things went OK for a while. I DMed a couple of short campaigns. We just swapped after some months, when the current DM got tired of prepping sessions.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, things went south with the group after some years. Won’t enter into details: people are shit, sometimes.</p>

<h3 id="university-years">University years</h3>

<p>Because of me being introverted, losing my only group of friends, etc, as soon as I finished high school, I asked my parents to let me attend university in Bologna, around 2 hours of train from my hometown. Just wanted to reset and restart, I guess. They agreed.</p>

<p>As I learnt those years in Bologna, putting physical distance between you and the place you feel deprived you of your joy… doesn’t always work, if the reason you’re unhappy comes with you.</p>

<p>But I digress. During university, I found an ad in a university board about a group looking for D&amp;D players. Another good amount of courage after, I went and played with them. They were all a bit older than me, students of at least 2 or 3 years of tenure. But we played for some sessions, and it went well! Until… we found out the DM only played with us to seduce one of the players, and after succeeding and becoming her boyfriend, he took a silly argument between a player and two others as a good reason to end the campaign. Spoiler: it wasn’t.</p>

<p>So, D&amp;D was over again, for me at least.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, a lot went on and changed with my life. I ended up in Rome, attending another university. Here I made some friends at least, with the aid of my currently best friend, whom I met online roleplaying in Neverwinter Nights 2.</p>

<p>We had a good time. I also discovered quite a lot of different TTRPGs than D&amp;D. We had good long campaigns of Sine Requie for instance. It’s a great Italian TTRPG about undead rising in 1944 during the WWII, and the world taking a whole different direction, with most of it being “Terre perdute” (= Lost lands) where you can only find undeads and rubbles, Italy becoming a Pope-ruled sort of modern-medieval society (“Sanctum Imperium”), Germany founding the IV Reich, etc.</p>

<p>But we also discovered Kult, a sweden game I absolutely encourage you to explore (current edition is called Kult: Divinity Lost) and gave me a lot of narrative ideas for my current D&amp;D homebrew setting.</p>

<p>For some time, I also came back to my hometown, due to family reasons. And while in Rome I mostly played as a PC, apart from some smaller D&amp;D campaigns, here I mastered a long, very appreciated campaign of Sine Requie, in the Sanctum Imperium setting. It was epic. The thing I remember most, is taking a premade oneshot, making one enemy NPC (an old woman who killed townsfolk, tore them to pieces, boiled them and made soap bars with their remnants) survive, and using her as the final boss of the campaign. But since she had become so powerful, the last session my players dropped their characters, and used pregenerated character sheets with some of the most important templar NPCs from the setting. They didn’t expect it, and it was spectacular.</p>

<h3 id="the-real-campaign-boss-covid-19">The real campaign boss: COVID-19!</h3>

<p>Up to this moment, all the campaigns I mastered or was a player in, were in-person plays. I mean, yeah, playing online was a sort of possibility, but almost unheard of, in Italy. Same thing for remote working.</p>

<p>In 2020, as you all may know, Covid came. Italy was especially hit, both by the infection, and by the painfully under-staffed and under-funded state of Italian national health service. So, from March 2020 to June, the country was completely shutted down. I was one of the lucky ones, being a software engineer: I resumed working, from home, and my job was especially busy (I worked in a portable spirometry devices manufacturer… business was booming with Covid).</p>

<p>But all the roleplaying halted. We tried resuming online, via Discord, but people didn’t have proper microphones, used very shitty webcams, and while playing we heard through our headset the whole house (brothers, sisters, parents, grandparents) instead of the only person playing with us. Also, I already stared at a screen for about 12 hours per day, going back to a call after dinner was hard.</p>

<p>After a couple of times, I proposed to stop, and everyone agreed.</p>

<p>So, Covid-19 was a mess for my TTRPG hobby. Even when Italy slowly tried returning to a sort of “normal” state of affair, it wasn’t in fact normal at all. Newspapers and media had shown us, for months, hospitals full of dying people. The infamous video of army’s vehicles in Bergamo, bringing hundreds of corpses of those who died of Covid-19 out of the hospital back in March 2020, was still vivid. Staying hidden in our homes for three months had imposed a heavy toll on our social minds.</p>

<p>I mean, it worked. I only caught Covid once, in 2021, after the vaccine, and it passed like nothing.</p>

<p>But, mentally speaking, it changed a lot. We couldn’t resume playing TTRPGs as before, even after the vaccine. We didn’t really fear for ourselves: it was for our elderly people, parents and granparents.</p>

<p>And even when, in 2022 onward, it seemed like there was normality back in the streets, too much time had passed, and nobody proposed to resume our campaigns. Habits had changed, at that point.</p>

<h3 id="our-bright-present">Our bright present</h3>

<p>My life had another turning point. As I said, I started working remotely during the pandemic, as we all did back in 2020. But, unlike almost everybody I know, I never stopped. Actually, my previous employer tried to force me, a couple of times. At the second time though, I just showed them the middle fing… I mean, I respectfully resigned, and went the freelancing / contractor way.</p>

<p>But I was still living in Rome, one of the most expensive city in Italy. Probably second, just after Milan. So, after a while, it didn’t really make sense to pay the exorbitant rent I was paying. I kept doing it for a while, living with my S.O., since she was working a normal office job (1 hour 30 minutes commute each way, every day… she really had patience, at the time).</p>

<p>In 2023 though, we had an opportunity to move back to my hometown. And after thinking, and thinking, and thinking, we said yeah, why not. Moving was slow and painful, as it always is. Especially because, since I started playing again (before the pandemic, at least), I now could afford buying books. And so I did, collecting all D&amp;D 5e books, and then some more from some other games (Sine Requie, Kult, …). I regret not buying 3e and 3.5e books at the time, and still look them up from time to time on eBay, wishing they didn’t cost 150€ each now.</p>

<p>But I digress. We moved, and back here in my hometown, after some months of IKEA trips and spending to my last dime to finish our new home… it was time to play again!</p>

<p>I evoked my old group (not the high school one) and they all agreed to play again. The campaign started in May 2024, and is still going strong today (October 2024).</p>

<p>What I didn’t mention is, although I haven’t played in the last years, I had some free time. And I invested some of that in writing my own setting. It started as a D&amp;D setting, but I don’t have almost any statistics for NPCs, just hundreds of pages of lore, setting, history, etc., so I guess it can be adapted to any fantasy pseudo-medieval game.</p>

<p>What I’d like to do, is introduce to you this setting, from time to time. If it looks interesting or inspiring to you, I’ll continue to do it.</p>

<p>Anyway, we’re playing in this setting right now. I’m not really in any way pushing the setting and the lore into our game: as some DM said some time in the past, probably Matt Colville, just let the story of your PCs intertwine with the setting, and they’ll get interested in it. More on that in another post, this one was long enough.</p>

<p>I’ll see what else I’d like to publish in the next days. We’ll see.</p>

<p>Thanks for reading, and until next time, I guess!</p>]]></content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Tabletop Role-Playing Games" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Humble beginnings]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why investing shouldn’t be boring</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/05/19/why-personal-finance-shouldnt-be-boring.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why investing shouldn’t be boring" /><published>2023-05-19T12:48:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-19T12:48:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/05/19/why-personal-finance-shouldnt-be-boring</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/05/19/why-personal-finance-shouldnt-be-boring.html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="vwce--chills-down-my-spine">VWCE &amp; Chill…s down my spine</h3>

<p><strong>I’ve been moderator of an Italian subreddit about personal finance</strong> for the last five years. It is the Italian subreddit <a href="https://reddit.com/r/ItaliaPersonalFinance" target="\_blank">r/ItaliaPersonalFinance</a>, and as you can guess, it is about the broad topic of personal finance.</p>

<p>There’s a lot more than what people think when we talk about handling your cash nest and investing it. The favourite motto of the ItaliaPersonalFinance subreddit is “<strong>VWCE &amp; Chill</strong>”: just buy 100% VWCE (an ETF covering most of the developed and developing countries in the world, market-cap weighted), sit back and relax, while your money will eventually grow (in about 10 years time).</p>

<p>But the analogy that comes to mind, when thinking about “VWCE &amp; Chill”, is getting prescribed generic pills at the first visit of a patient to their psychiatrist. The physician doesn’t know anything about the person in front of them, they don’t know their history, their thoughts, the depth of their possible illness, and still prescribe to “just take these pills and see how you feel”.</p>

<p>You may see some improvement, things can go nicely for a while; but in the end, the real effect of a mindless choice will manifest itself and blow in the face of the patient, that will visit another physician, maybe a better one, who will show the inner weakness of the choices of the first one.</p>

<p>That’s to say, it’s not a bad idea <em>per se</em>. It’s a much better idea than going to your bank and make them invest your money (want to gift 3-8% of your invested money each year in commissions?). It’s an even better idea than just opening your brokerage account and then buying some random, popular stocks, and expect them to grow without a single drop. But it’s not what the Latins called a <em>panacea</em>, a remedy for all possible personal finance issues. It’s more of a generic anti-inflammatory drug, to be administered with some care, and knowing we’re just treating symptoms, most of the times.</p>

<p>Enough with the medicine metaphors: let’s dig into the issues.</p>

<h3 id="some-issues-with-generic-investments-advice">Some issues with generic investments’ advice</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Everything’s changing faster than we realize</strong>
As some old sage man once said, humans tend to think as if their present self, their current desiders, dreams, ambitions, etc., will never change again, if not for some smaller adaptations as we get older. When some folk on Reddit tells us “Only invest in stocks if you’re not going to touch this money for 10 years at least”, we find great joy in spending that money into VWCE, since the idea of the next 10 years of our life being stable and financially secure is appealing and pleases the self. But reality often unveils the lies we tell ourself… even in a traumatic way, sometimes.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Being young doesn’t automatically mean you should invest in stocks</strong>
Common wisdom in the personal finance world tells us that young people should invest in stocks more (in percentage of their funds) than older folk. I think this is a huge simplification, and even plainly wrong in some cases.
In fact, I’m around 30 years old, and a lot changed in my life. Even something as my car, I sort of regret buying now, since I work from home and I don’t really need a vehicle in my own belongings any more. While five years ago I was absolutely certain I’d never own a house in my life, it looks like I will soon. And the list goes on.
<strong>Stocks are, from the return point of a view, very static assets</strong>. You should generally own them for a long period of time before you can safely say they will have given something in return: stocks tend to live through long periods of slow growth, and sudden catastrophic free falls, before recovering. Bonds, on the other hand, unless the emitter defaults or “cuts” the promised coupons, have a very specific time-frame (even Bond ETFs… although it’s a bit more complicated).
Also, generally speaking, <strong>young people tend to have a low saving rate, due to salaries being lower, and the best investment they should make with the little money they have, is learning new skills and tools</strong>, which can return a huge compound interest over time, instead of throwing the money into financial markets.
[For this specific idea, and the thoughts it provoked in me, I have to thank <strong>Paolo Coletti</strong>, an Italian youtuber active in the finance and investments world.]
But, as always, looking at the average young person doesn’t provide answers for a lot of different people coming from different backgrounds, families, living in wildly different part of the world. Don’t just take the generic advice: it could be tragically wrong for you.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Risk aversion is a real thing, and nobody can really assess their own until things go south</strong>
I think years of growing financial markets, especially with stocks, have altered the common perception of risk among everybody. I’ll make a gross simplification in the next lines, but bear with me: I think it’s needed as a wake up call for a lot of us.
<strong>Investing is stock is throwing your money at unknown people (the “market”), and expecting them to use it in unknown moves and make you earn more, but with no financial obligation to return any of the money given</strong>. Imagine having 80 or 100% of your hard earned cash in the hands of these people. Does it feel safe?
How about bonds? <strong>Bonds are a contract, but still, a slim one</strong>. There’s absolutely no guarantee the people you lend money to will effectively give it back. In the contract it is clearly stated that it’s their right to default on the promise, should things go wrong. And whether they’re using your money wisely or wasting it, is really out of your hands.
You’re betting on a bet safer than the casino’s, but still, it is betting. History of the last 50 years may show your bets are expected to give a nice premium. History of the last 100 years shows instead in what dangerous waters you’re swimming.
People <strong>can</strong> and absolutely <strong>will</strong> lose money when they’re betting. Not always, and that’s why we bet. And I’m not sure we can really assess our own risk aversion, just thinking about the hypotetical event of having our portfolio down 70% from when we bought it, unless we really are in that situation. Also because, it’s not like newspapers and media have a positive outlook on the economy when stock markets are so deep down the toilet: most probably, they’re talking about the end of finance as we know it, apocalypse and doom for the few crazy guys still holding stock ETFs. And it’s hard, almost impossible, to have a detached point of view and, instead of panic selling, buying more due to a one in a lifetime occasion of low prices.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="wrapping-up">Wrapping up</h3>

<p>I’m not advocating for financial advisors: the reality is, most of us don’t have enough to be a customer for these people, and other solutions (robo advisors, or even, God forbid, bank advisors) are generally too expensive to be worth it (at least where I live). I think everybody should invest some time into learning personal finance and investments, but it’s probably just a distant dream. We’ll see: for the time being, I encourage you, my dear reader, to rethink your risk tolerance/aversion, your asset allocation, and be aware of the fact that our lives change, multiple times per decade, and it could be better for you to have an elasticity in your investments, instead of a complete, static commitment on the best returning asset class.</p>]]></content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Personal finance" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[VWCE &amp; Chill…s down my spine]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My experience with trading</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/03/18/my-experience-with-trading.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My experience with trading" /><published>2023-03-18T14:02:41+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-18T14:02:41+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/03/18/my-experience-with-trading</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/personal%20finance/2023/03/18/my-experience-with-trading.html"><![CDATA[<p>Back in 2015, even before my whole professional career as a software engineer started, I became fascinated with the idea that, without even moving a single inch from my chair, <strong>I could become a profitable day-trader and just let that be my future full-time job</strong>.</p>

<p>The idea was born thanks to an Italian online community (<a href="https://www.finanzaonline.com" target="blank">Finanza OnLine</a>), one of the most toxic yet fascinating communities in personal finance, investments and, for about 90% of the traffic of the website, “trading”.</p>

<p>So, I gathered my hard-earned cash at the time (about 7k euros), opened a brokerage account in an Italian online bank, and…</p>

<p>Well, <em>of course</em> it didn’t end well. With that meager budget, brokerage commissions counted for about 0,2% of every transaction. For a “day-trader”, it’s simply not sustainable, even if somehow I could manage to guess a trade at least 60% of times (<em>spoiler: I could not</em>). <strong>I was chasing the gold fever, while my bank was selling me shovels</strong> and making a very passive, simple profit out of my dreams.</p>

<p>I learned a lot of terms and concepts day traders in the online community talk about. Technical analysis was one of them. Moving averages (simple, weighted…?), volumes, Relative Strength Index, MACD, and so on. I developed my own systems, but failed to even follow them consistently. I was just pursuing easy money, like a lottery, with a bit of a gambling habit.</p>

<p><strong>I ended up losing about 2 or 3k</strong>, can’t remember exactly. An overall expensive, yet cheap lesson, compared to what I could have lost years down the line, as a professional with a steady monthly income.</p>

<p>And most importantly, after that experience, <strong>I had learned a bunch of useful stuff</strong>. First of all, using an online broker to buy and sell stocks. The concepts of order limits, quantities, commissions, etc etc. Those all turned out to be quite handy, when studying investments and ETFs. Which I discovered in that same toxic community. There’s a very small, almost desert section of the forum about long-term investments and ETFs. And even though the content might not be much, discovering about the possibility of investing my own money with longer time horizons certainly started there.</p>

<p>Back to trading. <strong>I didn’t actually abandon the whole idea of “trading” there</strong>. Only one concept, which seemed interesting, stuck with me for a while. That concept is “algorithmic trading”.</p>

<p>In 2015, I knew almost nothing about programming. I could probably set up an extremely simple HTML page, or write some code in Pascal, perhaps. So, while exploring this whole fascinating, perilous world, I even tried writing some algorithms for a while. I used a proprietary Italian software called VisualTrader, but it didn’t really stick, and I couldn’t find a decent way to make it work as I wanted (due to my own limits, not the platform’s), so I gave up.</p>

<p>But years down the line, that idea came back. And then (about 2019), I could write complex programs! I had a look at some platforms, but in the end just wrote my own with barebone C# and .NET. The only external dependency was stocks data, which came for free from my broker at the time. Unfortunately, the broker changed rules after a while, and started charging about 20€/month for it - not worth it for me, since it was just a hobby.</p>

<p>Meanwhile though, I had developed a whole framework in .NET. It’s called <strong>Venice</strong>, and its core library is actually <a href="https://github.com/NandayDev/Venice" target="blank">open-sourced on GitHub</a>. I don’t think anybody but me has ever used it, so, don’t expect it working out of the box.</p>

<p>How did my algorithmic trading efforts go, by the way? Well, pretty poorly. Turns out in algo trading (as the cool kids call it), <strong>the hard part isn’t actually coding; it’s having a profitable idea which the market hasn’t already optimized away</strong>. And with my simple trading systems, after commissions and taxes, I haven’t found nothing really worthy. At the moment, I’m only passively gathering one-minute stocks data every day from a Raspberry Pi, in the hope I make use of it one day.</p>

<p>Turns out maybe I should just do what I’m really good at, which is software engineering, and let dreams of passive income through trading fade away, for the time being.</p>]]></content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Personal finance" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Back in 2015, even before my whole professional career as a software engineer started, I became fascinated with the idea that, without even moving a single inch from my chair, I could become a profitable day-trader and just let that be my future full-time job.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Planning your life and finances: worth it?</title><link href="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/thoughts/2023/01/26/planning-life-finances-worth-it.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Planning your life and finances: worth it?" /><published>2023-01-26T07:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-26T07:03:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.nanday.dev/blog/thoughts/2023/01/26/planning-life-finances-worth-it</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.nanday.dev/blog/thoughts/2023/01/26/planning-life-finances-worth-it.html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="ips-investor-policy-statement">IPS (Investor Policy Statement)</h3>

<p>These days, I’m setting some time aside to write my <strong>Investor Policy Statement (IPS)</strong>, inspired by <a href="https://www.retireinprogress.com" target="\_blank">Mr.RIP</a>, an Italian blogger and content creator, and his recent update about his old IPS, <a href="https://mr.rip/ips" target="\_blank">which you can find here</a>.</p>

<p>The aim of an IPS, as I intend it throughout this post, should be to plan your investments years ahead, starting from some <strong>objectives</strong>, then defining <strong>strategies</strong>, and, in the end, an <strong>asset allocation</strong>.</p>

<p>For instance:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>My objective is to reach retirement age around 65 years old with a decent safety nest of securities</em></li>
  <li><em>My strategy is putting aside 15% of my income and investing it in both index funds (or ETFs) and hand-picked stocks/bonds</em></li>
  <li><em>My asset allocation is 40% stock ETFs, 20% single stocks, 40% single bonds</em></li>
</ul>

<p>Mr. RIP also has a section about his philosophy of investments and investment details, but for simplicity I merged them into the strategy section.</p>

<h3 id="objectives">Objectives</h3>

<p>There’s only one caveat to this whole architecture: the act of starting from objectives is, to say the least, weak. <strong>I believe objectives are not an endurable asset throughout your life</strong>. Objectives mutate each year. I think Mr. RIP noticed this, since in <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/12ta_RURV99qFi0lxS-8Pgh5da3ee-XG9tWP1FHVST3c/edit" target="\_blank">his update to the IPS</a>, his new objectives are a lot broader and more generic than the original IPS.</p>

<p>What I’m coming to realize is this: <strong>planning and having specific objectives is not worth it</strong>. Unless we’re talking about something coming up in the next year or so, thinking you can really pursue a very narrow objective for 10 or more years without rethinking it, is <em>usually</em> wishful thinking.</p>

<p>At this point, the counterargument I usually hear is <em>Having an objective, and acting accordingly, is better than having none and just living day-by-day</em>. At a first reading it seems correct. A purpose gives you strength: if that purpose changes through the way, you may still have accumulated some resources (money usually) to invest it elsewhere and follow another purpose. I kind of agree about having this flexibility. But I can’t help but think that maybe, <strong>what you should have followed instead, is having that flexibility</strong>. Instead of giving yourself the illusion of an objective (“In 10 years time, I want to become financially independent!”), you could have planned something less specific, and reasonable (“In 10 years time, I want to have a good saving nest for whatever purpose I’ll find to spend part of it”).</p>

<p>But I understand, at this point, life would probably be emptier. As humans, we usually need a more powerful substance to fuel our life. Chasing the dream of opening that toys store where kids will come and cheer, instead of having the generic objective of being financially safe and flexible, sounds a lot better to our ears. And yet, I think for most of us, dreams and aspirations change each year. They rarely stick in a person’s life.</p>

<h3 id="happiness">Happiness…</h3>

<p>Thinking in broader terms, <strong>if your purpose is being happy, that resolves to two aspects</strong>, in the end:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Pursuing what makes us happy</li>
  <li>Avoiding what makes us unhappy</li>
</ul>

<p>And <strong>while having a very specific objective certainly fullfills number 1 greatly, it fails spectacularly at number 2</strong>. Chasing a dream is a road paved with difficulties and hardships. Doesn’t it make more sense to give up chasing a dream, and instead, just have some generic guidelines throughout your life? That way, you can still pursue happiness, while avoiding more moments of unhappiness along the way.</p>

<h3 id="-or-pain">… or pain?</h3>

<p>Yes. But…</p>

<p>Are we really wired that way?</p>

<p>This is a fundamental question. If, as human beings, we’re just built to pursue very specific dreams and fullfillment, does it even make sense to try avoiding having those dreams?</p>

<p>Siddhartha Gautama, better known as the Buddha, would probably say yes. <strong>All the original buddhist philosophy (as far as I understand it) revolves around escaping Dharma, the perpetual rotating engine of desire, fullfillment and the pain it brings</strong> (and of reincarnation in a more religious sense). Escaping desire surely seems like what we’re trying to achieve here. No dreams, just guidelines.</p>

<p>And yet, does it make sense? <strong>Isn’t the avoidance of pain, after all, pain</strong>? Escaping Dharma is a struggle which could be eternal. How can I escape my own very instinctual nature, without a fight so intense it will probably bleed me out of all energies?</p>

<p>In the end, <strong>accepting myself and my own nature seems more reasonable</strong>. Life is struggle, life is pain. And the caveat here is, whenever I’m not struggling, my own self will suffer anyway: after a brief moment of joy, hedonism adaptation will kick in, and life will become boring in my eyes. And I shall move on again, back to another struggle. <em>“He who hesitates is lost”</em>, they say, and for good reasons. Stasis kills the self.</p>

<h3 id="wrapping-up">Wrapping up</h3>

<p>I may have derailed a bit here. I think, in the end, we can extract two key takeaways:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Do have objectives</strong>, because that’s what your brain is wired to do, and that’s what’s going to bring you joy in the short term; but beware of the fact that those objectives will surely change, sooner rather than later;</li>
  <li><strong>Save up resources</strong> for your objectives, current or future ones: having that flexibility will help in any case.</li>
</ul>

<p>Until next time!</p>]]></content><author><name>Guido Cardinali</name></author><category term="Thoughts" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[IPS (Investor Policy Statement)]]></summary></entry></feed>